<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse of superstition with respect to the present times wherein the Church of England is vindicated from the imputation, and the the charge retorted not only on the papists, but also on men of other perswasions / by William Shelton ...</title>
            <author>Shelton, William, d. 1699.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1678</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 204 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 103 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A59650</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3097</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10846</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13786219</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13786219</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101809</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A59650)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101809)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 849:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse of superstition with respect to the present times wherein the Church of England is vindicated from the imputation, and the the charge retorted not only on the papists, but also on men of other perswasions / by William Shelton ...</title>
                  <author>Shelton, William, d. 1699.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24], 182 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.M. for Jonathan Robinson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1678.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. [24]</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Customs and practices.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Doctrines.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:101809:1"/>
            <p>IMPRIMATUR</p>
            <p>Hic Liber cui Titulus, <hi>A Diſcourſe of Superſtition,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>May 11. 1678.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Guill. Sill,</hi> R. P. D. <hi>Henr.</hi> Epiſc. <hi>Lond.</hi> à ſacris Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſticis.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101809:1"/>
            <p>A DISCOURSE OF Superſtition With reſpect to the PRESENT TIMES. WHEREIN The Church of <hi>ENGLAND</hi> is Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the Imputation, and the Charge retorted not only on the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo on men of other Perſwaſions.</p>
            <p>By <hi>William Shelton,</hi> Rector of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>James Colcheſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. M.</hi> for <hi>Jonathan Robinſon,</hi> at the Golden Lyon in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul's Church-Yard,</hi> MDCLXXVIII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:101809:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:101809:2"/>
            <head>To the RIGHT REVEREND FATHER in GOD, AND RIGHT HONOURABLE HENRY LORD BISHOP OF LONDON, One of His Majeſties moſt Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Privy-Council, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe your Lordſhip,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THere is none to whom I owe account of my ſelf and Studies, more than to
<pb facs="tcp:101809:3"/> your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> as my <hi>Dioce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſan.</hi> None to whom I more readily ſubmit this Eſſay, which endeavours to do Right to the <hi>Church of England,</hi> whoſe Honour and Security is ſo great a part of your <hi>Lordſhips</hi> care, as to challenge the acknowledgment of all Pens. The Moderation of our <hi>Church</hi> (which ought to be eſteem'd her Glory) in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding no farther from the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> than ſhe has receded from Primitive Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, is objected as a Crime, by the eager men of the <hi>ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our Firſt Reformers were
<pb facs="tcp:101809:3"/> Wiſe men, and (Thanks be to God) ſo are their Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors too. Their Wiſdom in the firſt compiling, and late Review of our <hi>Liturgy,</hi> has directed them to keep <hi>the mean between the Two Extreams, of too much ſtiffneſs in refuſing, and too much eaſineſs in admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting variations.</hi> So by the good Providence of God, have we been deliver'd from the <hi>ſuperſtitions</hi> of the <hi>Romiſh Church;</hi> and ſo have we been preſerved from a <hi>ſuperſtitious</hi> avoiding <hi>ſuperſtition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As the Kingdom of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> is famous for being the Balance of <hi>Europe;</hi> ſo is the
<pb facs="tcp:101809:4"/> 
               <hi>Church of England,</hi> for being, by a regular Reformation, well fix'd in a due diſtance between the <hi>ſuperſtitious</hi> addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> where <hi>Supremacy, Infallibility,</hi> and the <hi>Inquiſition</hi> compel men to <hi>ſwallow Camels,</hi> and the <hi>ſuperſtitious Abſtinences</hi> of thoſe who <hi>ſtrain at Gnats,</hi> and either will not Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the notion of a thing <hi>Indifferent,</hi> or will not rightly infer from it.</p>
            <p>To evince this, is the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of the following Tract, which in all humility I offer to your <hi>Lordſhips</hi> Patronage, being thereto embolden'd,
<pb facs="tcp:101809:4"/> by the Experience I have had of your <hi>Lordſhips</hi> Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor and Favour, which by how much the leſs I have me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited, I ought the more to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge.</p>
            <p>God Almighty preſerve your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> to a long <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidency</hi> in this <hi>Church:</hi> and bleſs the joint labours and cares of the Right Reverend my <hi>Lords the Biſhops,</hi> to ſuch an happy Repair of our Breaches; that neither the <hi>Wild-Boar,</hi> nor the <hi>Foxes,</hi> may ſpoil our Vineyard: to be ſuch a defence upon the <hi>Glory of this Church,</hi> that
<pb facs="tcp:101809:5"/> neither the <hi>Romaniſt</hi> nor <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratiſt,</hi> may ſtain or darken it. So prayeth,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips in all Humility and Obedience, <hi>W.</hi> SHELTON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:101809:5"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <label>SECTION I.</label>
               <item> THE Occaſion of this Diſcourſe. The <hi>Church of England</hi> charg'd with <hi>Superſtition.</hi> In the times of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> King <hi>James.</hi> The reproach reſtrain'd by a Canon, to no purpoſe. The Jealouſy en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creas'd in the beginning of <hi>Charles I.</hi> and in the time of the Covenant. The deſign of this Diſcourſe. Pag. 1</item>
               <label>
                  <hi>SECT. II.</hi> 
               </label>
               <item>The uſe of the word firſt inquir'd into: Then the nature of the thing. How Greek Authours uſe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.
<pb facs="tcp:101809:6"/> 
                  <hi>Smith</hi>'s ſelect Diſcourſe. <hi>Plutarch. Max. Tyrius. Antoninus.</hi> D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Hammond</hi>'s Tract of <hi>Superſtition</hi> conſider'd. What Latin Authors mean by <hi>Superſtitio. Tully</hi> oppoſes it to <hi>Religion. Lactantius</hi> not agreeing with him in the reaſon of the word. p. 11</item>
               <label>SECT. III.</label>
               <item> Other Etymologies. <hi>Superſtitio quaſi ſuper ſtatutum. Lucretius</hi> huffs at all Religion as <hi>ſuper ſtans. Nigidius Figulus</hi> account of the word. <hi>Seneca, Tacitus, Suetonius, Pliny</hi> take it in a bad ſenſe, ſo <hi>Feſtus</hi> and St. <hi>Paul. S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Auſtin</hi> differs not, who comprehends many particulars under this General, according to whom many <hi>ſuperſtitious</hi> obſervations obtain ſtill in the World. Three Definitions of <hi>ſuperſtition</hi> out of <hi>Aquinas. Zanchy, Ames</hi> to the ſame purpoſe. <hi>Religion,</hi> True Worſhip; <hi>Superſtition</hi> falſe worſhip. p. 18</item>
               <label>
                  <pb facs="tcp:101809:6"/>
                  <hi>SECT. IV.</hi>
               </label>
               <item> The Nature of the thing conſider'd in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Propoſitions. Firſt, <hi>Superſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is firſt in the Opinion, then in the practice.</hi> To which agree <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, Hooker, Falkener.</hi> The ſame practice ſuperſtitious or not, as the Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion is by which it is guided. This the Foundation of what follows. p. 28</item>
               <label>SECT. V.</label>
               <item> Second Propoſ. <hi>The Doctrines upon which the Conformity of the</hi> Church of England <hi>is eſtabliſhed, are not ſuperſtitious Opinions.</hi> Thoſe Doctrines are as follows. Firſt, <hi>All Circumſtances relating to the worſhip of God, are not particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly determin'd in H. Scripture. T. C.</hi> gainſays, but it is manifeſtly true. Our Adverſaries acknowledge and build upon it. p. 34</item>
               <label>
                  <pb facs="tcp:101809:7"/>
                  <hi>SECT. VI.</hi>
               </label>
               <item> Secondly, <hi>Some things (notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Scripture determinations) do ſtill remain Indifferent in their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</hi> This denied by <hi>Bradſhaw</hi> and <hi>Brook: Bradſhaw</hi> chang'd his mind, but his followers propagate his firſt Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion. A groſs miſtake. A Thing <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different</hi> not a mean between <hi>Good</hi> and <hi>evil,</hi> but between <hi>Commanded</hi> and <hi>forbidden.</hi> p. 40</item>
               <label>SECT. VII.</label>
               <item>
                  <hi> Brooks</hi> notion, <hi>Optimum eſt eligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum,</hi> not always true. In divers ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes no <hi>Beſt.</hi> Many diſhes at a feaſt. Many Inns in a Town. Many Shops in a City. He that ſtays till he know which is Beſt, will in many caſes never determine, becauſe he hath nothing to determine him but his own choice. The
<pb facs="tcp:101809:7"/> Ceremonies of our Religion not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſo <hi>Indifferent,</hi> but <hi>in ſpecie</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Commanded nor forbidden. p. 45</item>
               <label>SECT. VIII.</label>
               <item> Thirdly, <hi>The Church may make De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminations in things Indifferent.</hi> Scrupled by <hi>Brooke,</hi> whoſe Diſcourſe of <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> is again examin'd. The weakneſs and Unworthineſs of it detected. Denied alſo by others, <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt Diſcourſe,</hi> &amp;c. and <hi>Bagſhaw,</hi> but upon inſufficient grounds. p. 55</item>
               <label>SECT. IX.</label>
               <item> This acknowledged by the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> in their <hi>Directory, Confeſſion of Faith.</hi> Other Authors that have writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſince. Acknowledged alſo by the <hi>Independents</hi> in their Confeſſion of Faith, 1658. p. 66</item>
               <label>
                  <pb facs="tcp:101809:8"/>
                  <hi>SECT. X.</hi>
               </label>
               <item> Fourthly, <hi>Where the Governours of the Church have power to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, they ought to be obey'd. Zanchy</hi> and <hi>Calvin</hi> on our ſide. When <hi>Zanchy</hi> would not have theſe things impos'd, yet he would have them yielded to (if impos'd) rather than any man ſhould quit his Miniſtry. p. 71</item>
               <label>
                  <hi>SECT. XI.</hi> 
               </label>
               <item>
                  <hi> Calvin</hi> of the ſame mind. Much for a ſtated Liturgy and Ceremonies, which though he would have few, yet thoſe he finds fault with, do not now obtain in our <hi>Church.</hi> What he did not like, he would have born with. As the <hi>Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plice</hi> in Biſhop <hi>Hoopers</hi> caſe, and Unleaven'd Bread at <hi>Geneva.</hi> p. 80</item>
               <label>
                  <pb facs="tcp:101809:8"/>
                  <hi>SECT. XII.</hi>
               </label>
               <item> Beſides theſe <hi>M. Durell</hi> cites about 40. Foreigners all of the ſame Judgment. As were alſo our Countreymen, <hi>T. C. Humfrey Rainolds, Knewſtubs,</hi> others. And of late <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Baxter.</hi> Theſe Teſtimonies concluded with <hi>St. Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe,</hi> and <hi>St. Auſtin</hi>'s determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. p. 87</item>
               <label>SECT. XIII.</label>
               <item> Fifthly, <hi>It is lawful for the Church to appoint ſignificant Ceremonies.</hi> This denied by N. C<hi rend="sup">ts</hi>. How they dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer from Sacraments. The Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians require <hi>ſitting</hi> at the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per becauſe <hi>ſignificant.</hi> Their pretence of the Example of Chriſt not ſufficient. Becauſe, p. 93</item>
               <label>
                  <pb facs="tcp:101809:9"/>
                  <hi>SECT. XIV.</hi>
               </label>
               <item> Firſt, That Example does no more oblige in this, than in other Circumſtances of Time and place, unleſs in the <hi>ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cancy</hi> of it, which then is as much <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious</hi> as our kneeling. For ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, They have not Example for the ſame manner of ſitting. Thirdly, Not certain whether they have Example for any manner of ſitting at all. p. 100</item>
               <label>SECT. XV.</label>
               <item> They uſe another <hi>ſignificant</hi> Ceremony in the Covenant and conſent they require of people whereby they ſhould own their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter. <hi>Worceſterſhire</hi> Agreement gives account of it. Diſtinction be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Diſcipline and Worſhip will not help them. p. 108</item>
               <label>
                  <pb facs="tcp:101809:9"/>
                  <hi>SECT. XVI.</hi>
               </label>
               <item> Upon theſe Grounds the <hi>Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> not <hi>ſuperſtitious,</hi> unleſs the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Ceremonies be too great. Which hath been complain'd of without Cauſe, and ſome of them acknowledge in our favour. A Digreſſion about the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Ceremonies. Or unleſs our Rites be requir'd as ſomewhat more than <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different.</hi> In which the Prefaces to our Liturgy vindicate us. p. 112</item>
               <label>SECT. XVII.</label>
               <item> Two Objections. 1. Ceremonies impos'd as <hi>Indifferent</hi> are not ſo. So they were once believ'd. But now ſome <hi>N. C<hi rend="sup">ts</hi>.</hi> think not ſo of them. Anſwer. Where no Law, no Tranſgreſſion. Not forbid in the ſecond Command, nor elſewhere. The Surplice, and Kneeling, and the Croſs particularly conſider'd. p. 123</item>
               <label>
                  <pb facs="tcp:101809:10"/>
                  <hi>SECT. XVIII.</hi>
               </label>
               <item> 2 Obj. Though in Nature Indifferent, yet ſome Accidents may render it ſinful to impoſe or practiſe them. They are thought by <hi>Bagſhaw</hi> to be laid as ſnares for tender Conſciences. If ſo, it would be Tyranny rather than ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. But it blaſphemes Dignities ſo to think. The Accidents conſider'd: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are offenſive: becauſe they come from <hi>Papiſts.</hi> The law of not giving offence does not diſoblige the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject from obedience in things in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves lawful. Nor does it diſable the Magiſtrate from making laws in things <hi>Indifferent.</hi> The abuſe of <hi>Popery</hi> ſignified nothing to <hi>T. C.</hi> in his own caſe. The ſecond General Propoſition concluded. p. 132</item>
               <label>
                  <pb facs="tcp:101809:10"/>
                  <hi>SECT. XIX.</hi>
               </label>
               <item> Third Propoſition. <hi>The Opinions that are ſuperſtitious are rejected by the Church of England.</hi> Divers Objections againſt <hi>Popery</hi> beſides <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition,</hi> but that now to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd. They are <hi>ſuperſtitious.</hi> Firſt, in making their Ceremonies neceſſary parts of Gods worſhip. <hi>Pius IV.</hi> Creed impos'd upon all Biſhops, makes all the Doctrines of <hi>Trent</hi> neceſſary to ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. They equal Traditions to the written word, and ſo introduce falſe Doctrines. They teach for Doctrines the Commands of men, and ſo are <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious.</hi> p. 144</item>
               <label>SECT. XX.</label>
               <item> Secondly, They aſcribe an efficacious ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctity to their Ceremonies. They worſhip the Croſs with <hi>Latra,</hi> and affirm that
<pb facs="tcp:101809:11"/> it ſcares away the Devil, drives away diſeaſes, and ſanctifies the things on which it is made. This is <hi>ſuperſtition</hi> to expect effects as by divine Inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which we have no warrant to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect. <hi>Eſtius</hi> endeavours to ſalve the matter, but not to ſatisfaction. They teach that the Sacraments confer Grace <hi>Ex opere Operato,</hi> and that is <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious. Bellarmines</hi> diſtinction between <hi>opus operatum,</hi> and <hi>ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantis,</hi> to their prejudice. p. 154</item>
               <label>SECT. XXI.</label>
               <item> Thirdly, Their Doctrine of <hi>Merit</hi> is <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious. Bellarmine</hi> aſcribes Merit and ſatisfaction to good Works. His famous acknowledgment to the contrary. We own a neceſſity of good works, but exclude Merit. Whatever elſe is any where done upon a Religious account, farther than Religion ought to be concern'd, is <hi>ſuperſtitious.</hi> The
<pb facs="tcp:101809:11"/> 
                  <hi>Church of England</hi> not guilty in any of theſe Caſes. p. 163</item>
               <label>SECT. XXII.</label>
               <item> The Fourth Propoſition. <hi>There are ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious Omiſſions of which men may be guilty, when they ſeem greatly to abhor ſuperſtition.</hi> A Negative <hi>Superſtition. A ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious fearfulneſs of which</hi> Lord <hi>Bacon</hi> and St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> complain. Such was that of the <hi>Jews</hi> who would not defend themſelves on the Sabbath day. Of the Souldiers in <hi>Sfetigrade.</hi> The N. C<hi rend="sup">ts</hi>. have reaſon to examine whether their <hi>Abſtinence</hi> be not ſuch. To ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain from that which is lawful, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving it Unlawful, this undue opinion of Religious Matters is <hi>ſuperſtitious.</hi> The Concluſion. p. 171</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:101809:12"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>PAge 95. line 9. for</hi> where inſignificant, <hi>read</hi> wherein ſignificant, <hi>p. 149. l. 13. for</hi> reſt <hi>r.</hi> reſts; the leſſer faults are left to the ingenuity of the Reader to correct or pardon.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <p>THere is lately publiſhed the ſeventh Edition of a Body of Divinity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> By the moſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Father in God, <hi>James Uſher,</hi> late Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Armagh,</hi> to which is added his Life, containing many remarkable paſſages never be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Extant. Sold by <hi>Jonathan Robin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> at the Golden-Lyon in St. <hi>Paul's Church-Yard.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:101809:12"/>
            <head>A DISCOURSE OF Superſtition With reſpect to the PRESENT TIMES, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>THE prejudices and diſaffecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons<note place="margin">Sect. 1.</note> which have alienated ſo many from the Communion of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> owe themſelves to no Original more; than to an Opinion taken up, that ſome Uſages in our Church are <hi>Superſtitious;</hi> An Opinion ſtrongly concluded, but upon weak grounds, and by a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs very illogical. For when the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:101809:13"/> Adverſaries of our Order and Peace, have amply repreſented, how jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous God is of his Honour, how ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely he hath threatned the breach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of the ſecond Commandment, and how ſorely he hath puniſhed the Idolatry of the Jews; in the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of theſe things to our Times, <hi>Superſtition</hi> and <hi>Idolatry</hi> are frequently join'd, as equally forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in that Commandment, and without more proof the <hi>Church of England</hi> is ſuppoſed guilty of <hi>Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition,</hi> and good people are exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to come out of her, upon pain of partaking of thoſe Plagues which Idolaters have reaſon to fear.</p>
            <p>From the times of Queen <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi> down to our days, <hi>Superſtition</hi> hath been laid to our Charge. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Hooker</hi> acknowledges and reſents it.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſiaſtic. Pol.</hi> Book 5. §. 4.</note> 
               <hi>So it is judged our Prayers, our Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, our Faſts, our times and places of publick meeting together for the Worſhip
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:101809:13"/> and Service of God, our Marriages, our Burials, our Functions, Elections, and Ordinations Eccleſiaſtical, almoſt what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever we do in the exerciſe of our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, according to Laws for that purpoſe eſtabliſhed, all things are ſome way or other thought faulty, all things ſtained with Superſtition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One of the <hi>Treatiſes</hi> that were ſent abroad (as it were to give new light to a new World) 1660. under the name of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>William Bradſhaw,</hi> is about things <hi>Indifferent,</hi> where he thus ſpeaks in the Marginal Notes.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Notes on the fifth Chapt.</hi> of things Indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent.</note> 
               <hi>The Doctors of</hi> Oxford <hi>ask, what hurt can a wiſe Man ſee in a ſquare Cap and a Surplice? Indeed there is no outward hurt or evil in it, but it muſt be conſidered, whether there be not any inward hurt therein; for if it can be proved, that by them the Souls of many are poiſoned with</hi> ſuperſtitious <hi>conceits, then it is apparent that they have inward hurt in them.</hi> This is but a ſuppoſition, but it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:101809:14"/> dogmatically, <hi>The Ceremonies</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid. <hi>Notes on Chap.</hi> 8.</note> 
               <hi>in Controverſy have been and are, the ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial means and occaſion of the Schiſm of many Hundred Browniſts, of much</hi> Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition <hi>in many Thouſand Ignorant Proteſtants, and of Confirmation of many Infinites of wilful Papiſts in their Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try.</hi> He concludes the Treatiſe thus: <hi>The Ceremonies in Controverſy are either excellent parts of our Religion</hi> (which he not yielding muſt believe the other part of the Disjunction) <hi>or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious parts of Superſtition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the dirt that was caſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Church of England,</hi> in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of King <hi>James</hi> his Reign, that he might be out of love with her. A reproach of which the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation</hi> of 1603. was ſo ſenſible (for though that Treatiſe came firſt out, a little after the Convocation, yet the ſuſpicion was rife before) that they paſs this Canon among<note place="margin">Canon 6.</note> others: <hi>Whoſoever ſhall hereafter af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:101809:14"/> the Rites and Ceremonies of the</hi> Church of England, <hi>by Law eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed, are wicked, Antichriſtian or</hi> Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious, <hi>&amp;c. Let him be Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,</hi> &amp;c. This Canon did not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain the petulancy of Cenſorious men, for beſides Mr. <hi>Bradſhaws</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence; in the defence that D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges</hi> makes for Biſhop <hi>Morton,</hi> it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Burges</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer Rejoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Chap. 4. §. 1.</hi>
               </note> that the N. C<hi rend="sup">ſts</hi> of thoſe times did thus argue. <hi>The Ceremonies of the</hi> Church of England <hi>have been and ſtill are abuſed to Idolatry and</hi> Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition <hi>by the Papiſts.</hi> And <hi>that we</hi>
               <note place="margin">Id. ib. §. 4.</note> 
               <hi>cannot be thought ſincerely to have repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of that Idolatry and Superſtition, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept we caſt away with deteſtation all the Inſtruments of it.</hi> Once more, they ſay, <hi>That a ſuperſtitious conſtruction is</hi>
               <note place="margin">Id. ib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 79.</note> 
               <hi>made of our Croſs, not only by the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, but by our own Canons and Canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Impoſers of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe Jealouſies did but fly in the dark during King <hi>James</hi> his
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:101809:15"/> Reign, but ſoon after <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Firſt</hi> came to the Throne, he recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved divers Complaints of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: The <hi>Parliament, Anno</hi> 1628.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ruſhworth</hi> Hiſtorical Collections, <hi>p. 526.</hi>
               </note> complains of Idolatry and <hi>Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> as ſome of thoſe <hi>heinous and cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſins, which were the undoubted Cauſe of thoſe evils that were fallen upon them.</hi> The <hi>Remonſtrance</hi> which the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons<note place="margin">Id. ib. p. 621.</note> of the ſame <hi>Parliament</hi> made againſt the then <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> expreſſes their fears concerning <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of Religion.</hi> A while after Mr. <hi>Rouſe</hi> makes a Speech concerning Religion, wherein he deſires it may be conſidered, <hi>what new paintings are laid on the old face of the Whore of Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon.</hi> How the <hi>See of</hi> Rome <hi>does eat</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ib. p. 645, 646.</note> 
               <hi>into our Religion, and fret into the banks and walls of it:</hi> for a remedy of which, he propounds the expedient of a <hi>Covenant, to hold faſt God and Religion, to which Covenant he would have every man ſay</hi> Amen. This man does not
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:101809:15"/> (it is true) ſpeak of <hi>Superſtition,</hi> but he is underſtood to mean it, by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Orator of the ſame Houſe (Mr. <hi>Pym</hi>) who complains <hi>that the Law</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ib. p. 647.</note> 
               <hi>was violated in bringing in</hi> ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Ceremonies.</hi> After whom, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the ſame Seſſion (Sir <hi>John Eliott</hi>) apprehends a fear of ſome<note place="margin">Ib. p. 649.</note> Biſhops then in place, that if they ſhould be in their power, they might be in danger of having Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion overthrown, becauſe <hi>ſome of them were Maſters of Ceremonies, and laboured to introduce new Ceremonies into the Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After thoſe eager Debates, the motion for a <hi>Covenant</hi> ſlept for ſome years, but was renewed again in the Unhappy Times of the <hi>Fatal Parliament.</hi> In the times when it was a great part of the Impeach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt the Great <hi>Arch-Biſhop of Canterbury,</hi> that he had <hi>traiterouſly</hi>
               <note place="margin">Artic. of Impeach. 7. 10.</note> 
               <hi>endeavoured to alter and ſubvert Gods true Religion by law eſtabliſhed in this
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:101809:16"/> Realm, and inſtead thereof to ſet up</hi> Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh ſuperſtition <hi>and Idolatry,</hi> and that he <hi>traiterouſly endeavoured to recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile the</hi> Church of England <hi>with the</hi> Church of Rome. In theſe times it was that Mr. <hi>Rouſe</hi>'s motion ripen'd up to a <hi>Solemn League and Covenant,</hi> wherein they obliged themſelves to endeavour the Extirpation of <hi>Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Prelacy,</hi> and <hi>Superſtition.</hi> By which words the <hi>Covenanters</hi> (as ſome of them have ſince declar'd) believe themſelves obliged againſt Conformity; for, this reaſon they give in a Book they call <hi>a Sober and Temperate Diſcourſe concerning the Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of words in Prayer,</hi> &amp;c. in which the Title of one of their Chapters is: <hi>The Miniſters Third Reaſon,</hi> viz.<note place="margin">Chap. 10.</note> 
               <hi>why they do not meddle with the Common Prayer</hi> (as are the words of the Chapter) <hi>is, becauſe they have ſworn to endeavour a reformation in worſhip, and to endeavour to extirpate Superſtition.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:101809:16"/>
            <p>Nothing now can be more evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, than that both of old, and in our times <hi>Superſtition</hi> is objected to us. It does not come in my way to condemn, nor do I take upon me to juſtify the practiſes of all particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar perſons; I concern my ſelf only in the legal Eſtabliſhments of our Church, and they would little need a vindication, if men would take the pains to enquire into the nature of <hi>Superſtition;</hi> for they would ſoon find the Innocence of our Rites would defend themſelves from this ſuſpicion. But it is our Unhappineſs that we have to deal with men who take things upon truſt, who are not eaſily undeceived, becauſe they will maintain a Concluſion, before they have examined the premiſes: ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving <hi>Superſtition</hi> to be a word that ſignifies ſomewhat bad, they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn us without a Tryal, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they know what it means,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:101809:17"/> conclude us guilty of <hi>Superſtition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have waited ſome while in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation, that ſome abler Pen would engage in this Argument, but not finding that of late days, the Nature of <hi>Superſtition</hi> has been parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly and fully diſcovered or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, I have now undertaken the task, in which becauſe I deſire to be underſtood, I labour for no other ornament of ſtile than perſpicuity: And without farther Preface I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to enquire, what is this <hi>Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition</hi> with which the <hi>Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> is ſo much upbraided.</p>
            <p>There is no Precept in the Holy Scripture that forbids <hi>Superſtition</hi> by that name, nor does any ſacred Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor mention it, except St. <hi>Luke</hi> in two places to be conſidered in due time, when I examine how the word is uſed in other Authors; For by this Method, I conceive, I ſhall beſt accompliſh my deſign, if</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:101809:17"/>
            <p>Firſt, I enquire into the uſe of the Word. And ſecondly, into the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the thing ſignified by ſuch a Word.</p>
            <p>1. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (by which the Greeks<note place="margin">Sect. 2.</note> expreſs'd that which we now com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly call <hi>Superſtition</hi>) ſignifies moſt literally a ſervice perform'd to God or to a Daemon, rather out of fear than love; <hi>An over-timerous and dreadful apprehenſion of the Deity,</hi> as the learned <hi>Smith,</hi> who alſo calls it<note place="margin">Select Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtit. <hi>p. 26. &amp; 36.</hi>
               </note> a <hi>compound of Fear and Flattery;</hi> ſuch an <hi>apprehenſion of God in the thoughts of men, as renders him grievous and burden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome to them.</hi> But however this may be the primary ſenſe of the word, yet that it hath been transfer'd to ſignifie more largely, is evident from Greek Authors. <hi>Plutarch</hi> in his Tract, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, conſtantly diſcourſes of it, as of an extream to Religion, to which he oppoſes A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſm as the other extream; Thus
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:101809:18"/> he begins, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Ignorance of God from the beginning hath run in Two Channels, one way to Atheiſm, and the other way to Superſtition.</hi> And after he had in many like expreſſions, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed them to one another he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Some have run ſo far from</hi> Superſtition, <hi>till they have over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhot themſelves into</hi> Atheiſm, <hi>having neglected</hi> Religion <hi>which is the mean be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween both.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Maximus Tyrius</hi> as plainly oppoſes<note place="margin">Diſſertat. 4ta.</note> the <hi>Religious,</hi> and <hi>Superſtitious</hi> man. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>A Religious man is the Friend of God, A ſuperſtitious man is a Flatterer of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Antoninus</hi> gives this Character of<note place="margin">Lib. 6. §. 30.</note> himſelf, He was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Religious without Superſtition.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:101809:18"/>
            <p>The Incomparable D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Hammond</hi> does (I know) purſue the Etymo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy and Original Notion of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in the former part of his little Tract of <hi>Superstition;</hi> where he gives ſeveral Interpretations of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and afterwards gives theſe ſenſes of the Compound word.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>It is taken in general for Religion or Worſhipping God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>For the worſhip of deify'd dead men, and Angels which the Heathens took to be True Gods.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>For any part of Divine Worſhip which for fear of vengeance from God, any Worſhipper perform'd to him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>For a trembling fear of Gods pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment due for every ſin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>For the uſe of Magical Spells.</hi> From whence he concludes the Modern uſe of the word improper; but whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther proper or improper, becauſe it is uſe that gives the rule for our manner of ſpeaking, therefore that
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:101809:19"/> muſt be conſidered: And that the word is uſed for ſomewhat undue in the worſhip of God, he himſelf ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledges in theſe words. <hi>That which men ſee thoſe of another perſwaſion do; which they like not, or think them not bound to, they call it ſtraight their Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that thus Authors have made uſe of this word, will more appear by conſidering the Latin word, <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitio.</hi> Concerning whoſe Etymo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy all Criticks are not agreed. <hi>Tully</hi> diſcourſes at large both of the name and thing, and he is the firſt among the Latin Authors now ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant, for ſo far as I can find, that ſo tranſlates the Greek Word: for if <hi>Nigidius Figulus</hi> (of whom by and by out of <hi>A. Gellius</hi>) were before him, yet I ſuppoſe he hath no entire Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume now extant. I therefore take ſome particular notice of what <hi>Tully</hi> ſays in this Matter. When he had
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:101809:19"/> given ſome natural Account of the Multitude of Gods that were ſo much talkt of in thoſe Ages, and of the <hi>Superſtitions</hi> that took riſe from the Fables of the Poets concerning them, he proceeds to diſtinguiſh between <hi>Religion and Superſtition,</hi> in memorable words. <hi>Cultus Deorum</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cicero do Natura De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orum lib. 2.</note> 
               <hi>eſt Optimus idem<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> caſtiſſimus at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſanctiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimus, pleniſſimuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> pietatis, ut eos ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per purâ integrâ incorruptâ &amp; mente &amp; voce veneremur. Non enim philoſophi ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum, verum etiam Majores noſtri</hi> Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitionem à Religione <hi>ſeparaverunt. Nam qui totos dies precabantur &amp; immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>labant, ut ſui liberi ſibi ſuperſtites eſſent,</hi> Superſtitioſi <hi>ſunt appellati, quod nomen patuit poſtealatius. Qui autem omnia quae ad Deorum cultum pertinerent, diligenter pertractarent &amp; tanquam relegerent, ſunt dicti</hi> Religioſi, <hi>&amp;c. It a factum eſt in</hi> Superſtitioſo <hi>&amp;</hi> Religioſo, <hi>alterum vitii Nomen, alterum laudis. The beſt, and pureſt, and moſt holy worſhip that we
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:101809:20"/> can give to God, is to ſerve him with à pure and uncorrupt heart and voice. For it was not only peculiar to Philoſophers, but our Forefathers alſo made a difference between</hi> Religion <hi>and</hi> Superſtition, <hi>for they who prayed all day long and offer'd Sacrifice that their Children might ſurvive them, were called</hi> Superſtitious; <hi>A word which afterwards was extended to a larger ſignification: But</hi> Religious <hi>men had their name from their diligence and care in reviewing what pertained to Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Worſhip. And hence it came to paſs, that in the ſetled uſe of theſe words,</hi> Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition <hi>was counted a Crime,</hi> Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion <hi>a praiſe-worthy thing.</hi> According to which diſtinction he had ſaid before: <hi>Superſtitione facile eſt liberare,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Id. ibid. lib. 1.</note> 
               <hi>cum ſuſtuleris omnem vim Deorum: niſi forte</hi> Diagoram <hi>aut</hi> Theodorum <hi>qui omnino Deos eſſe negabant, cenſes</hi> Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitioſos <hi>eſſe potuiſſe. Horum enim ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiae non modo</hi> Superſtitionem <hi>tollunt in qua ineſt Timor inanis Deorum, ſed
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:101809:20"/> etiam</hi> Religionem <hi>quae Deorum cultu pio continetur. It is an eaſy matter to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure men from</hi> Superſtition, <hi>if you will make them</hi> Atheiſts; <hi>Unleſs you think ſuch Atheiſts as</hi> Diagoras <hi>and</hi> Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorus <hi>could be tainted with it, whoſe O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions did not only root out</hi> Superſtition, <hi>which contains in it a vain and needleſs fear of God, but true Religion too, which conſiſts in a right worſhip of the Deity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The reaſons which this learned Heathen aſſigns of the names and differences between <hi>Superſtition</hi> and <hi>Religion, Lactantius</hi> likes not, and<note place="margin">Lactant. de verâ ſapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Cap. 28.</note> therefore when he had derived <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion à Religando;</hi> of <hi>Superſtition</hi> he ſpeaks thus: <hi>Superſtitioſi vocantur ii, qui ſuper ſtitum memoriam defunctorum co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lunt, aut qui parentibus ſuis ſuperſtitibus colebant Imagines eorum domi tanquam Deos penates. Nam qui novos ſibi ritus aſſumebant, ut in Deorum vicem mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuos honorarent quos ex hominibus in coelum receptos putabant, hos</hi> Superſtitioſos
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:101809:21"/> 
               <hi>vocabant; eos vero qui publicos &amp; An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquos deos colerent,</hi> Religioſos <hi>nomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant, unde</hi> Virgilius,</p>
            <q>Vana ſuperſtitio veterúm<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ignara Deo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>They were counted</hi> Superſtitious <hi>who did honour to the memory of the dead, or who while their Parents were alive, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped their Images as if they were Houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold Gods: for they who took up any new Rites, in giving honour to dead men, whom they thought to be taken up to Heaven among the Gods, were ſo called; whereas they were eſteemed</hi> Religious, <hi>who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined themſelves to the worſhip of thoſe who were anciently reputed for Deities. Hence</hi> Virgil <hi>introduces</hi> Evander, <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing himſelf to</hi> Aeneas, <hi>that the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour he did to</hi> Hercules <hi>did not deſerve the name of</hi> Superſtition.</p>
            <p>There want not other Etymolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies<note place="margin">Sect. 3.</note> of this word. <hi>Iſidore</hi> is quoted
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:101809:21"/> for this, <hi>Superſtitio quaſi ſuperſtatuta</hi>
               <note place="margin">M. Delrii Diſqu iſ. Magic. lib. 1. Cap. 1.</note> 
               <hi>obſervatio. An unſtatutable, unwarrant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able obſervation. Alii dicunt à ſenibus, quia multis annis ſuperſtites per aetatem delirant:</hi> then is introduced <hi>Lucre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius, qui ſuperſtitionem dicit ſuperſtantium rerum,</hi> i. e. <hi>coeleſtium quae ſuper nos ſtant,</hi> for which theſe Verſes are quoted where he huffs at all <hi>Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>Humana ante Oculos foedi cùm vita jaceret,</l>
               <l>In terris oppreſſa gravi ſub Relligione,</l>
               <l>Quae caput è Coeli regionibus oſtendebat,</l>
               <l>Horribili ſuper aſpectu mortalibus inſtans.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>(So not only <hi>Delrio,</hi> but <hi>Turnebus</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo<note place="margin">Adverſar. lib. 10. Cap. 26.</note> reads that Verſe which others read thus,</p>
            <q>Horribili aſpectu ſemper mortalibus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtans.)</q>
            <p>according to <hi>Lucretius,</hi> all <hi>Religion,</hi> becauſe it concerns it ſelf in things above us, (with which that <hi>Atheiſt</hi> thought we had nothing to do) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:101809:22"/> the name of <hi>Superſtition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whatever the firſt Reaſon of this appellation might be, thus much is certain, that in ordinary uſe, it ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified ſomewhat undue in Divine Worſhip; and of this <hi>Tully</hi> was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware, when he made the acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment, of which <hi>Lactantius</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got to take notice. <hi>Quod Nomen pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuit poſtea latius.</hi> Alſo <hi>Nigidius Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulus</hi> in his Comment upon the old Verſe,</p>
            <q>Religentem eſſe oportet, Religioſum nefas.</q>
            <p>takes <hi>Religioſus</hi> in an ill ſenſe as all<note place="margin">A. Gellii Noct. At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tic. lib 4. Cap. 9.</note> one with <hi>Superſtition. Religioſus is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellabatur qui nimiâ &amp; ſuperſtitioſâ Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gione ſeſe alligaverat, ea<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> res vitio aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignabatur. He who was</hi> ſuperſtitious <hi>in his Religion (which was counted a Crime) was called a</hi> Religious <hi>man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seneca</hi> expreſſes the Import of this<note place="margin">Senec. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. 123.</note>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:101809:22"/> word well, according to the Greek: <hi>Superſtitio error inſanus eſt, amandos ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met, quos colit violat, quid enim intereſt utrum Deos neges an infames? Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is a wild kind of error, it is afraid of him who ought to be loved, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honours him whom it worſhips, for what difference is there whether you deny God or blaſpheme him?</hi> In a former Epiſtle he diſcourſes thus. <hi>Audiat quemadmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum</hi>
               <note place="margin">Id. Epiſt. 95.</note> 
               <hi>ſe gerere in ſacrificiis debeat, quam procul reſilire à moleſtis</hi> ſuperſtitioni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus. <hi>Nunquam ſatis profectum erit, niſi qualem debet Deum mente conceperit. He who deſires to underſtand himſelf and his Religion, let him retire as far as he can from troubleſome ſuperſtitions. No man will proceed well in Religion, who hath not right Conceptions of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In a like ſenſe do other Latin Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors uſe the word, when they up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braid Chriſtian Religion under that name, as apprehending it a falſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. So <hi>Tacitus</hi> when he ſpeaks of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:101809:23"/> 
               <hi>Nero</hi>'s laying the blame of the burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Rome</hi> upon the Chriſtians, calls<note place="margin">Hiſtor. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt. lib. 15.</note> their way <hi>Exitiabilis Superſtitio, A pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilent Superſtition. Suetonius</hi> alſo in the life of the ſame <hi>Nero,</hi> calls the<note place="margin">Vit Neron. Cap. 16.</note> Chriſtians, <hi>Genus hominum ſuperſtitionis novae &amp; maleficae. A ſort of men of a new and miſchievous Superſtition.</hi> And <hi>Pliny</hi> to <hi>Trajan,</hi> gives Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion the ſame name though with ſomewhat a ſofter Epithet. <hi>Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio prava &amp; immodica, An Immoderate Superſtition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is then the Account I gather out of Heathen Authors, moſtly hitherto: the ſenſe they had of a Deity perſwaded them not only that he ought to be worſhipped, but alſo that every kind of ſervice would not be acceptable to him. The right worſhip of God (that which they ſo apprehended) they called <hi>Religion,</hi> that which was undue, and therefore unacceptable, paſſed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:101809:23"/> the name of <hi>Superſtition.</hi> Even as <hi>Feſtus</hi> did apply the name to the Religion of the Jews, as eſteeming<note place="margin">Acts 25. Acts 17.</note> it not the beſt way of worſhip. And St. <hi>Paul</hi> more truly, did ſo reprove the Idolatry of <hi>Athens.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When the World was better in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in the Notion of a Deity, and in the manner of worſhip that was due to him, we find the word ſtill in uſe among Chriſtian Authors. <hi>Lactantius</hi> hath been offered already. St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> comprehends Idolatry and many other particular Cuſtoms un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this Term. <hi>Superſtitioſum eſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">De Doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nâ Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anâ lib. 2. Cap. 20.</note> 
               <hi>quicquid inſtitutum eſt ab hominibus ad facienda &amp; colenda Idola, pertinens vel ad colendam, ſicut Deum, creaturam par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>témve ullam Creaturae, vel ad conſulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones &amp; pacta quaedam ſignificationum cum Daemonibus placita at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> foederata, qualia ſunt molimina Magicarum artium,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Ex quo genere ſunt Haruſpicum &amp; Augurum libri, etiam omnes ligaturae
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:101809:24"/> at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> remedia quae medicorum diſciplina con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnat, ſive in praecantationibus ſive in quibuſdam notis quas characteres vocant.</hi> Idolatry and conſulting with the Devil, or any kind of Witchcraft: The practices of Soothſayers, that would pretend to foretel future E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents by the flying of Birds or En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trails of Beaſts: Thoſe Charms that are deſigned for the Cure of Diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, of which no natural or phyſical account can be given: Theſe and divers like Obſervations he taxes with <hi>Superſtition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſome of thoſe (or others like them) which St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> there menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, obtain ſtill in the World: <hi>viz.</hi> If Rats do any miſchief, to be afraid of that as an ill Omen of ſome death or diſaſter in the Family: And ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other as unaccountable. If it rain or ſnow ſuch a day, or be fair ſuch a day (as <hi>Candlemas,</hi> and <hi>Swithin,</hi> and others) then the future part of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:101809:24"/> the year will be ſo or ſo. Theſe Obſervations have upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count been eſteemed <hi>Superſtitious,</hi> becauſe they are taken to be an indication of the pleaſure of God as to future Events, whereas we have no aſſurance that they are a ſufficient indication. And it may deſerve enquiry, whether the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom of praying God to bleſs per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons when they <hi>ſneeze,</hi> were not originally <hi>ſuperſtitious.</hi> I determine not in this caſe, becauſe <hi>ſneezing</hi> hath been ſometimes reckoned a Diſeaſe, and then praying for ſuch an one, is of the ſame import, with praying for any one in danger: but I make the doubt, becauſe <hi>ſneezing</hi> hath been ſometimes reckoned an Omen of good or bad luck, and St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> mentions this in the ſame place where he ſpeaks of <hi>Millia ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſſimarum</hi>
               <note place="margin">Id. ibid.</note> 
               <hi>obſervationum,</hi> when a man does <hi>redire ad lectum ſi dum ſe calceat ſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutaverit.</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:101809:25"/> If a man chance to <hi>ſneeze while he is putting on his ſhooes he muſt to bed again.</hi> Theſe and a Thouſand ſuch obſervances as theſe, are deem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to have a relation to God, when it cannot be proved, and are therefore judg'd <hi>ſuperſtitious,</hi> ſo far as there is any Religion placed in them.</p>
            <p>I proceed no further in examin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the uſe of the word, than to give Three Definitions of it, from Three men of ſeveral Ages, and ſeveral ways and Opinions, but ſuch as do all amount to one and the ſame pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aquinas</hi> gives it thus: <hi>Superſtitio</hi>
               <note place="margin">Secunda ſecundae qu. 92. Art. 1, &amp; 2.</note> 
               <hi>eſt vitium Religioni oppoſitum ſecundum exceſſum, quo quis divinum exhibet cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum vel cui non debet, vel non eo modo quo debet.</hi> And in the next Article con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes. <hi>Multae ſunt ſuperſtitionis ſpecies, ut Indebitus veri Dei cultus, Idololatria, Divinationes &amp; varia obſervationum ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nera.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:101809:25"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Zanchy</hi> to the ſame purpoſe. <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtum</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tom. 4. lib. 1. Cap. 17.</note> 
               <hi>eſt ſuperſtitionem eſſe Religioni oppoſitam &amp; per exceſſum.</hi> He adds, <hi>Unde etiam fit ut omnis falſus cultus ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitio appelletur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ames</hi> alſo ſays thus. <hi>Superſtitio eſt</hi>
               <note place="margin">Medul. Theolog. lib. 2. Cap. 13.</note> 
               <hi>quâ Deo cultus indebitus exhibetur,</hi> and again, <hi>Superſtitio dicitur exceſſus Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gionis.</hi> The ſum of all which is, as <hi>Atheiſm</hi> is a <hi>defect</hi> of <hi>Religion,</hi> ſo is <hi>Superſtition</hi> an extream on the other hand, an <hi>Exceſſive Religiouſneſs,</hi> when men go beyond their bounds in Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Worſhip; ſo that all falſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip goes under the name of <hi>Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition.</hi> A man may be righteous over-much, and over-much wiſe, ſo may he alſo be, not too holy or too good, yet too <hi>religious,</hi> when he exceeds, and practiſes in matters of Religion upon Opinions falſe and unworthy of God.</p>
            <p>This hath been the uſe of the word in approved Authors of divers
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:101809:26"/> Ages. It hath ſometimes been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined to particular practices, as Magick and Enchantments; but upon a general reaſon, becauſe theſe are undue mixtures in Religion, for ſo both in Heathen and Chriſtian Authors this difference is commonly aſſigned between them. <hi>Religio eſt</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ubi prius.</note> 
               <hi>veri Cultus, ſuperſtitio falſi,</hi> as <hi>Lactan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> hath it. When we worſhip God aright that is <hi>Religion,</hi> when by any undue additions we corrupt <hi>Religion,</hi> in all thoſe things we are <hi>ſuperſtitious.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. The Enquiry into the Nature<note place="margin">Sect. 4.</note> of the thing ſtill remains. Whereby does it appear, whether the worſhip we here, or others elſewhere perform to God be regular and <hi>Religious,</hi> or exceſſive &amp; undue, and ſo <hi>ſuperſtitious?</hi> The Reſolution I give to this que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, I form into theſe Propoſitions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Superſtition is firſt in the Opinion, and thence influences upon the practice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>The Doctrines upon which the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:101809:26"/> of the Church of</hi> England <hi>is eſtabliſhed, are not ſuperſtitious Opinions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>The Opinions that are indeed ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious (ſuch as are divers that obtain in the Papacy and elſewhere) are rejected by the Church of</hi> England.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>There are ſuperſtitious Omiſſions, of which men may be guilty, and that then, when they ſeem to have a great Zeal againſt Superſtition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1. <hi>Superſtition is firſt in the Opinion before it can have any influence upon the practice.</hi> Practices are unlawful, when they tranſgreſs the Commands by which they are obliged, but <hi>ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitiouſly</hi> unlawful they cannot be, unleſs they proceed from ſuch Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions: Hence it comes to paſs, that the ſame practices are ſometimes <hi>ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious</hi> and ſometimes not, according as mens Opinions are, by which they are perſwaded to them. So is the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between the <hi>Ch. of England,</hi> and of <hi>Rome,</hi> in the uſe of the <hi>Croſs,</hi> in
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:101809:27"/> 
               <hi>kneeling</hi> in the act of receiving, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as will afterwards appear. I am not alone in thus ſtating the Notion of <hi>Superſtition. A ſuperſtitious act is that</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Biſhop</hi> Dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham (Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton) <hi>Sermon on</hi> 1 Cor. 11. 16.</note> 
               <hi>which is founded upon a ſuperſtitious Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion. It was not meerly the Phariſees often waſhing, but their Opinion of ſome eſpecial purgation thereby, which Chriſt reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in them. Nor was it the having an Altar for which</hi> St. Paul <hi>reproved the</hi> Athenians, <hi>when he called them ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious, but the opinion of honouring a God thereby they knew not whom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To a like purpoſe, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Hooker, Superſtition is when things are abhorred</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity. <hi>Book 5. §. 3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>or obſerved, with a zealous or fearful, but erroneous relation to God.</hi> And in words juſt before. <hi>Superſtition is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways join'd with a wrong opinion touching things divine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Conformably to both theſe, ſays a late learned Author, <hi>All Supersti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Falkener</hi> Libert. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſt. B. 1. Chap. 5. Sect. 2. §. 7.</note> 
               <hi>or other ſinful honour of the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, must be founded in embracing
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:101809:27"/> thoſe falſe apprehenſions and corrupt Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines which our Church rejects.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> refers to the inward ſenſe and apprehenſion of our minds: or if it muſt be diſtinguiſhed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the thoughts of the mind, and the paſſions of the Soul; it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that fear ariſes from ſuch opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions and apprehenſions as admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter to it. Yea though <hi>ſuperstition</hi> be (as hath been ſaid) an exceſs of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and though this exceſs may diſcover it ſelf in the practices of men, yet the reaſon and that which occaſions this exceſs, is in the Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</p>
            <p>Falſe Notions and apprehenſions of God, tempt men to try by undue ways to pleaſe him. Men have a conceit, that ſuch ſervices are more grateful to him than they are: Or, there is <hi>a ſuperstitious</hi> obſervation of ſome Accidents, as <hi>Prognosticks</hi> of Events, becauſe of an Opinion ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:101809:28"/> up, that God Almighty does by ſuch ſigns declare his pleaſure or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure.</p>
            <p>In all theſe Caſes, the Firſt Seat of <hi>Superstition</hi> is in the <hi>Opinion,</hi> and from thence it is derived into pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice; for did theſe falſe Opinions which thus miſlead men, ceaſe by a better information of the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, the practices and obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances that depend on them would alſo ceaſe; or if they were continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, they would be hypocritical, or vain, or any thing rather than <hi>ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitious.</hi> For Example: It is <hi>ſupersti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious</hi> (ſay we) to worſhip an Image, or to pray a Soul out of Purgatory, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> becauſe they are falſe and <hi>ſuperstitious</hi> Opinions that induce men ſo to do. If it may be ſuppoſed that men who opine right, who do not in their judgment yield more to an Image than they ought, and who do not in truth believe Purgatory; may
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:101809:28"/> yet perform the ſame Ceremonies, and make the ſame prayers; I ask then, for what reaſon are theſe things done? If not for this reaſon, becauſe men are of opinion that the Image deſerves it, that the dead may be profited by their Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; then is it a vain and ridiculous piece of Pageantry. Or if ſome po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litick reaſon, and ſecular Intereſt tempt men theſe ways; what they do may be excuſed from <hi>Superstition,</hi> becauſe it is not intended for the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of God, and ſo is not perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as a part of his Worſhip, but it is otherwiſe faulty, becauſe by preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Religion they advance their Intereſt, and <hi>gain</hi> becomes their <hi>Godlineſs.</hi> If in truth there be any Religious intendments in theſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances, then this is that which plainly renders them <hi>ſuperstitious,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they Originally proceed from <hi>ſuperstitious Opinions.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:101809:29"/>
            <p>This I have firſt ſaid, becauſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this depends the Vindication I deſign of the Uſages of the <hi>Church of England.</hi> For, if what is done in Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Worſhip, be not otherwiſe <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perstitious,</hi> but as it proceeds from and is directed by <hi>ſuperstitious Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;</hi> then if it can be evinc'd, that we are not guided by any ſuch Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, it will follow that our Rites and Ceremonies are void of <hi>ſupersti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> And this I truſt to make ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in what next follows.</p>
            <p>2. <hi>The Doctrines upon which the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sect. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Conformity of the Church of</hi> England <hi>is establiſhed, are not ſuperstitious Opinions.</hi> Of which matter I give this Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, which I ſhall take to be ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, till by an Enumeration of ſome other particulars, of which I am not aware, it be made appear, that there are ſome other Doctrines that may be ſuſpected of <hi>ſuperstition,</hi> which the <hi>Church of England</hi> in juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:101809:29"/> of her Conformity is obliged to maintain.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>All Circumstances relating to the Worſhip and ſervice of God, are not par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly determined in the word of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Therefore, notwithstanding the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminations of the Holy Scripture, ſome things do remain Indifferent in their own Natures.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>The Governours of the Church have power to make Determinations in things Indifferent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Therefore people are bound to obey their Governours in ſuch their Determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>It is not unlawful for Church-Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours to appoint ſome ſignificant Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies.</hi> Theſe are the foundations upon which we ſtand; upon which our Governours require, and upon which we practiſe Conformity, and none of theſe are <hi>ſuperstitious</hi> Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Wherefore in the application of theſe Generals to our Times and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:101809:30"/> ſtate of things, we conclude, the Rites and Ceremonies of the <hi>Church of England</hi> not being for their num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber burdenſome (of which in due time) are not in their nature and kind <hi>ſuperstitious.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1. <hi>He who judges all Circumstances relating to the publick worſhip of God not particularly determined in the word of God, is not ſuperstitious in that Opinion.</hi> For this is ſo plainly and manifeſtly true, that it is a ſhame for any man to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny it. There hath been (I know) an Axiome among <hi>Cartwrights</hi> Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, <hi>That nothing ought to be establiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Church, which is not comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the word of God.</hi> This they thought plainly warranted by the manifeſt words of the law, <hi>about ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to or diminiſhing from the word of God.</hi> Now (adds M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Hooker) theſe</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Book 3. §. 5.</note> 
               <hi>men having an eye to a number of Rites and Orders in the Church of</hi> England, <hi>ſuch as the Ring in Marriage, the Croſs,</hi> &amp;c.
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:101809:30"/> 
               <hi>thought by the one only ſtroke of that Axiome to have cut them off.</hi> And <hi>T. C.</hi> is quoted as arguing thus. <hi>You which</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ib. §. 2.</note> 
               <hi>diſtinguiſh and ſay, that Matters of Faith and neceſſary to ſalvation, may not be to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerated in the Church, unleſs they be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly contained in the word of God, or manifeſtly gathered; But the Ceremonies, Order, Diſcipline, Government in the Church, may not be received againſt the word of God, and conſequently may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, if there be no word againſt them, although there be none for them: You I ſay diſtinguiſhing in this ſort prove an evil divider.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To all which there needs no other Anſwer than what M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Hooker</hi> gives. <hi>Let that which they do hereby intend, be granted them; let it once ſtand as conſonant to reaſon, that becauſe we are forbid to add to the Law of God any thing, or to take ought from it, therefore we may not for matters of the Church make any law more than is already ſet down in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ib. §. 6.</note>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:101809:31"/> 
               <hi>who ſees not what ſentence it ſhall enforce us to give againſt all Churches in the World, in as much as there is not one, but hath had many things eſtabliſhed in it, which though the Scripture did never com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, yet for us to condemn were raſhneſs.</hi> He goes on to give the Example of the Church of God in the time of our Saviour inſtead of all others.</p>
            <p>If this ratiocination be weak, they who ſuſpect it have great reaſon to ſhew us out of Scripture an exact form of Church-Government; but inſtead of doing ſo, they only argue that ſo it muſt be, without directing us to the place where it is. To which I again oppoſe M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Hookers</hi> words. <hi>As for thoſe marvellous diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid. ad fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem.</note> 
               <hi>whereby they adventure to argue, that God muſt needs have done the things which they imagine were to be done: I muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs I have often wondred at their boldneſs herein. When the queſtion is, whether God hath delivered us in Scripture (as
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:101809:31"/> they affirm he hath) a compleat, particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, immutable form of Church-Polity, why take they that other both preſumptuous and ſuperfluous labour, to prove he ſhould have done it: There being no way in this caſe to prove the deed of God, ſave only by producing that Evidence wherewith he hath done it? But if there be no ſuch thing apparent upon record, they do as if one ſhould demand a Legacy by force of ſome written Teſtament, wherein there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no ſuch thing ſpecified, he pleads that there it muſt be, and brings Arguments from the love of the Teſtator, imagining that theſe proofs will convict a Teſtament to have that in it, which other men can no where by reading find.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It will appear in the proceſs of our arguing, that the very men who would inſinuate to the diſparage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our Rites, that Divine Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip muſt have a Divine Warrant, for Circumſtances as well as for ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, have not themſelves been
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:101809:32"/> guided by this Opinion, but have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken a liberty in their <hi>Directorian</hi> or Dictatorian way, which they have denied to others: And becauſe I ſhall by and by bring them as wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes for us and againſt themſelves, I reſpit yet a little their farther Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction in this matter.</p>
            <p>2. <hi>Notwithſtanding the Determinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sect. 6.</note> 
               <hi>of the Holy Scripture, there do ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main ſome things in their own nature Indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent;</hi> and in this Opinion there is no <hi>Superſtition.</hi> It might reaſonably be thought, that this Propoſition is ſo evident, that no man who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to learning will deny it. But ſo it is, that the power of Church-Governours may be reduc'd in a manner to nothing, ſome there have been, who will not own any thing <hi>Indifferent</hi> in theſe matters. I meet with two who have maintain'd this Aſſertion, and I preſume they are the ſame whom Biſhop <hi>Saunderſon</hi>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:101809:32"/> means, when he ſpeaks of ſome of<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Saunderſon</hi> de Obliga. Conſcient. praelec. 6. §. 23.</note> this Opinion. <hi>Duo praeſertim, alter ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cujus nominis apud ſuarum partium homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes Theologus, alter è proceribus Regni laicus.</hi> Thoſe Two, I conceive, muſt be M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Bradſhaw</hi> and the Lord <hi>Brooke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall not do M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Bradſhaw</hi> right, if I do not acknowledge, that D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
               <note place="margin">Burges <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>join'd.</hi> Ch. 2. §. 9.</note> 
               <hi>Burges</hi> tells us, <hi>he revers'd his Opinion of things Indifferent.</hi> Surely he had great reaſon to do it. That he was once of the Opinion which I faſten on him, muſt not be denied. One of his Treatiſes Reprinted 1660. is Of the <hi>Nature and uſe of things Indifferent.</hi> Where he ſtates the Caſe thus: <hi>A</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chap. 2.</note> 
               <hi>thing Indifferent is a mean between good and evil, ſo that whatſoever is Indifferent is neither good nor evil, whatſoever is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good or evil is not indifferent.</hi> After this he avers, <hi>that no Action of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chap. 8.</note> 
               <hi>whether it be Moral or Ceremonial, is Indifferent, but either good or evil;</hi> and
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:101809:33"/> again, <hi>No Ceremony of Religion is In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid.</note>
            </p>
            <p>A groſs and palpable miſtake and unworthy of a man ſo cryed up for his learning, the more pardonable indeed becauſe he acknowledged his Error: but becauſe they who Reprinted him, were not ſo juſt to his Memory as to inſert that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment, and becauſe they for whoſe ſake he was reprinted, have not, it may be, that reſpect for D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Burges</hi> as to read him, I muſt animadvert on it as I find it, and anſwer, That no conſidering man can think, that when we uſe an <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different</hi> Rite, we mean that we do neither good nor evil. No ſure, that which is <hi>Indifferent</hi> in its Nature, may be in its uſe Neceſſary. We uſe it as being by ſufficient Authority com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded thereto, and therefore up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch reaſons as juſtifie us that we do well; if we are miſtaken in our
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:101809:33"/> Judgment, and have no ſufficient reaſon for what we do, it is ill done.</p>
            <p>But this plainly we mean by a thing in its Nature <hi>Indifferent,</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what which is not <hi>in ſpecie</hi> comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of God, and ſo is not abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly neceſſary, nor is it ſo forbid, therefore not ſimply Unlawful. This M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Bradſhaw</hi> might have known to have been our Notion of a thing <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different,</hi> for ſo M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Hooker</hi> (at whom he ſometimes nibbles) had told him. <hi>The nature of things Indifferent is, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be commanded nor forbidden, but left free and Arbitrary.</hi> He inſtances quickly after. <hi>When many meats are ſet</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ. Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,</hi> Book 2. §. 4.</note> 
               <hi>before me, all are Indifferent, none Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful, I take one as moſt convenient. If ſcripture require me ſo to do, then is not the thing Indifferent, becauſe I muſt do what ſcripture requires. They are all In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different, I might take any; ſcripture does not require me to make any ſpecial
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:101809:34"/> choice of one, I do notwithſtanding make choice of one, my diſcretion teaching me ſo to do.</hi> Now though eating of this diſh rather than another, cannot be ſaid, after my choice is made, to be neither good nor evil, (for I chuſe diſcreetly or indiſcreetly) yet before my choice determin'd me to one, they were both <hi>Indifferent</hi> (ſo in their nature they ſtill remain) neither commanded, neither forbidden, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther neceſſary, neither unlawful in its own Nature.</p>
            <p>So in the Circumſtances of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, after my choice is determined by the Command of my Superiors, theſe things are not ſo <hi>Indifferent</hi> as that I do neither well nor ill in my obedience. Before they had deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined they found theſe things <hi>Indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent</hi> in their Nature, their diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion having guided them to make choice of ſuch a Veſture, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as they apprehended convenient, now that
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:101809:34"/> becomes neceſſary as to uſe, which at the ſame time remains <hi>Indifferent</hi> in its Nature.</p>
            <p>The Lord <hi>Brooke</hi> by a little Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphyſicalneſs<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sect. 7.</hi> Diſc. open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cop. <hi>Ch. 5.</hi>
               </note> goes farther, and from this principle, <hi>Optimum eſt ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per eligendum,</hi> endeavours to prove this Concluſion. That <hi>there is nothing Indifferent</hi> in Re &amp; in ſe, <hi>but to our Underſtandings ſome things ſeem ſo, for want of good light, but in the things them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves every thing,</hi> pro hic &amp; nunc, <hi>is either Neceſſary or Unlawful.</hi> It may ſeem harſh to ſay that a man is not always obliged to do that which is <hi>beſt.</hi> Where there is an apparent dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference and inequality in the matter of our actions, how far a man may ſatisfie himſelf to do that which is <hi>good,</hi> though he do not always that which is <hi>beſt,</hi> I digreſs not to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine. The Aſſertion may be foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon another reaſon and ſtate of things, and upon that I build and
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:101809:35"/> ſay, There is a Truth in this Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, <hi>A man is not always obliged to do that which is beſt;</hi> the reaſon is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in ſome Caſes there is no <hi>Beſt,</hi> but the ſeverals that fall under deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beration are alike, no more Intrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick Good or Evil in one than another, but any of them if it were alone, were ſufficiently eligible and ſatisfactory. Now if in every action of a mans life he muſt not proceed, till he can find a difference where none is to be found; If a man muſt no where act, till he ſee clearly what is beſt to be done, this muſt needs fill the minds of men with In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite ſcruples and perpetual anxie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: And after a man is ſatisfied that this is good and lawful and fit to be done, yet muſt he demur and take heed he do it not, leſt perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture ſomewhat elſe were better to be done in the room of it. I give Inſtances whereby it will appear
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:101809:35"/> we are not left to endleſs doubts in all Caſes.</p>
            <p>I am at Table and have many Diſhes of meat before me which pleaſe me well, I care not to eat of all, but make my choice as it may happen, I cannot ſay it is <hi>Beſt</hi> to eat of this or that, either that which is commended to me, or that which is next me, or ſome like accident determines my choice, and if I had eaten ſomewhat elſe it would have been equally to my ſatisfaction. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, ſhould I ſit ſtill and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute with my ſelf thus? I muſt do that which is <hi>Beſt,</hi> therefore I muſt conſider of every Diſh by it ſelf, and diligently obſerve all the differences between them, and if I cannot clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcern which is beſt of all, I muſt ſit ſtill till I can: ſo I might loſe my Dinner, and when I riſe, ſhould find my mind as unſatisfied as my belly. Or, I am travelling and take
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:101809:36"/> up in a Town where I never was before; I ſee divers fair Inns before me, know none; nor have I any manner of reaſon to prefer one to another. I go to one as it happens, not out of this principle that I muſt do that which is <hi>beſt,</hi> for they are all alike, all <hi>Indifferent,</hi> and if I chuſe not till I certainly know which is beſt for me, I may lie in the ſtreets all Night. Once more, I go to <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> to buy ſomewhat that I want, without any other Intereſt or Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance than my money. Many Shops ſell the ſame Commodities, I can give no reaſon (but this only, that I muſt buy ſomewhere) why I call at the ſign of the <hi>Sun,</hi> or the <hi>Moon,</hi> the <hi>Lyon,</hi> or the <hi>Bear.</hi> They are all alike, only ſome accident (without full perſwaſion that I do that which is beſt) determines me. And an Hundred ſuch like Caſes happen in the Courſe of Affairs.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:101809:36"/>
            <p>Now in all theſe, what ſhall we ſay to <hi>Bradſhaw?</hi> Cannot theſe things be <hi>Indifferent,</hi> unleſs what I do be neither good nor bad? No ſure. Till I have made my choice, it is <hi>Indifferent,</hi> becauſe I am under no Command in theſe Caſes, but am left perfectly to the conduct of my own diſcretion. And what ſhall we anſwer to <hi>Brooke?</hi> Muſt I not ſtir till I know which is <hi>Beſt?</hi> There is no <hi>Beſt</hi> nor <hi>Worſt.</hi> If I diſcern any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenience on one ſide more than on the other, then is there a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and I am unadviſed if I do not conſider it: but where I diſcern no difference, and yet ſcruple till I be ſatisfied which is <hi>Beſt,</hi> I ſhall ſcruple till Doomeſday if I ſhould live ſo long, becauſe I have nothing to determine me but my own choice. It remains then, that there are things <hi>Indifferent</hi> in their own Nature. Where there is no Antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:101809:37"/> Command to make ſuch an Action neceſſary, nor Antecedent prohibition to make it unlawful, it is <hi>Indifferent</hi> in it ſelf, not between good and evil, but between com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded and forbidden, between abſolutely neceſſary and ſimply un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful.</p>
            <p>I have laid my Foundation thus low in a Conſideration of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of things, becauſe the Object<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors I deal with goe thus far. It is not neceſſary to our Cauſe to affirm, that the Ceremonies of Religion in Controverſy (the <hi>Surplice</hi> and <hi>Croſs, &amp;c.</hi>) are altogether ſo <hi>Indifferent,</hi> as that there ſhould be no more reaſon to determine rather to one, than there is to take one Inn or Shop ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than another. Theſe Inſtances were produc'd to ſhow where the Rule fails, <hi>Optimum eſt ſemper faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endum,</hi> and to prove that there are things <hi>Indifferent</hi> in their own nature.
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:101809:37"/> To which I add, that ſome Rites and Ceremonies of our Religion are ſo too, as I prove by this Irrefraga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Argument. Whatſoever is <hi>in ſpecie,</hi> neither commanded nor for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden (<hi>i. e.</hi> antecedently to hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane laws) is a thing <hi>Indifferent</hi> in its own nature. But the <hi>Surplice</hi> and the <hi>Croſs,</hi> and <hi>Kneeling,</hi> &amp;c. are <hi>in ſpecie</hi> neither Commanded nor for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden. <hi>Ergo</hi> they are <hi>Indifferent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They who deny the <hi>Major</hi> fight with their own ſhadows, and gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay out of a ſpirit of oppoſition; for we perſiſt in this (and they know it) that we mean nothing elſe by a thing <hi>Indifferent</hi> in its own nature, but ſomewhat left undetermin'd in the Holy Scripture. They who deny the <hi>Minor,</hi> muſt prove theſe things in the uſe of them forbid in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture; which if they ſhall endeavour to do, I doubt not but to pronounce them <hi>ſuperſtitious,</hi> and ſhall in the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:101809:38"/> Concluſion prove it. In the mean time, becauſe Negatives are hard to be proved, it concerns them to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute us by producing the Texts which forbid them: which Texts if they be no other than the <hi>ſecond Commandment,</hi> or that in <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 2. a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>will-worſhip,</hi> or <hi>Matthew 15. Teaching for Doctrines the Commandments of men,</hi> or ſome ſuch like theſe, then I demand farther, In as much as the <hi>Surplice,</hi> &amp;c. are not named in any of theſe places, by what good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, by what Demonſtrative Syllogiſm ſhall it be proved from ſuch a Text that it is not lawful to wear a <hi>Surplice?</hi> Here now will be the failure, they quote Texts from whence they declaim, but they do not argue cloſely and cogently. We know we do not add to the word of God (whether they do not <hi>Ipſi viderint,</hi> and I ſhall anon endeavour to open their Eyes) We do not teach
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:101809:38"/> for <hi>Doctrines</hi> the <hi>Commands of men.</hi> We do not urge humane Impoſitions upon account of Divine Inſtitution (any otherwiſe than as it is the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment of God to obey Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity) Wherefore when ſuch a Text is one of the premiſes, we fear not with Confidence to aver, that this cannot be a good Concluſion. <hi>Ergo,</hi> to wear a <hi>Surplice</hi> is not <hi>Indifferent</hi> in its Nature but a Sin. But of this a little more hereafter.</p>
            <p>Now I farther proceed and ſay, The <hi>Church of England</hi> does not reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on theſe things ſo <hi>Indifferent</hi> as to partake nothing of the nature of good or evil (which is <hi>Bradſhaws</hi> falſe Notion) or ſo <hi>Indifferent</hi> that all other things that may come in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition with them are as equal to them as one Shop or Inn may be to another. For Example. <hi>Kneeling</hi> is not ſo <hi>Indifferent</hi> that there is no more to be ſaid for it, than for lying
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:101809:39"/> along. A <hi>White Garment</hi> not ſo <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different</hi> as that any other colour would be altogether as grave and decent: but therefore <hi>Indifferent,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe undetermin'd in Scripture. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs, when the Governours of the Church have deſcended to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, what is expedient to be done in theſe matters, the determinations which they have made, have not been by chance as a man goes to his Inn, but they have proceeded ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Rules of Chriſtian Prudence (and it is to be hoped they may be allowed to do ſo, as well as the <hi>Aſſembly</hi> who in their <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectory</hi> ſo profeſs, as will preſently be ſaid) The general Rules of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, Order, and Edification have ſet them their bounds. According to the beſt of their Wiſdom, they have judged ſuch and ſuch Impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons expedient, and therefore have ſo determin'd concerning them.</p>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:101809:39"/>
            <p>Which determinations when they are once made, ſo far as the Lord <hi>Brooks</hi> Notion is true, it ſerves our turn very well, <hi>Optimum eſt faciendum.</hi> We have ſo much Reverence for our Superiours, as to judge they have determin'd us to that, which they thought moſt fit and expedient: then for our own practice, we ſtill eſteem theſe things <hi>Indifferent</hi> in their nature, but neceſſary as to uſe. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſatisfied that the Holy Scripture does not forbid ſuch uſages, we count them lawful. Being alſo ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied that our Governours command them, now by virtue of a Law In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervening, they are neceſſary to us, becauſe we are commanded to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey our Governours in all lawful things.</p>
            <p>Theſe things pertaining to the Propoſitions that next follow, I go on.</p>
            <p>3. <hi>It is no ſuperſtitious Opinion to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sect. 8.</note>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:101809:40"/> 
               <hi>that the Church may make determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations in things Indifferent.</hi> Our fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mention'd <hi>Lord Brooke</hi> boggles here, I muſt therefore conſider what he ſays.</p>
            <p>Firſt, He concludes thus. <hi>The</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ib. Chap. 6.</note> 
               <hi>Church hath no power to make any one thing Indifferent in it ſelf.</hi> (That, ſay I, ſhe need not do, for ſhe finds them <hi>Indifferent.) Again</hi> (he ſays) <hi>we cannot ſay the Church hath power to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine what is Indifferent. In things that ſeem Indifferent, where neither of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creams is neceſſary, there (eſpecially where both are doubtful</hi>) [he conceives] <hi>the Church hath not power to determine to ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther extream. As ſuppoſe Black and White Colours ſhould be doubtful, whether both or either, or neither were lawful; In this Caſe</hi> (ſays he) <hi>for ought I yet ſee, the Church hath no power to determine any one ſo doubting, either to Black or White; the reaſon is, becauſe neither is neceſſary, there being ſo many Intermediate Colours
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:101809:40"/> between both.</hi> That is as much as to ſay (if theſe things be applyed) Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters may be determin'd neither to a <hi>White Surplice,</hi> nor to a <hi>Black Gown,</hi> becauſe there are other Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, and rather than the Church ſhall determine to one, Miniſters ſhall be left to their liberty, to dreſs themſelves in a Fools Coat. But he goes on to cut ſhort the Churches power. <hi>When one of the extreams, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween which we waver as Indifferent, is neceſſary to be embrac'd, as in moſt caſes it is, here all the power lawful</hi> (as he conceives again) <hi>can do no more but reſolve which of the two extreams is beſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And is not this hitherto pretty well? A <hi>ſurplice</hi> cannot be ſaid to be neceſſary, becauſe a man may wear a Gown, or Cloak, or Coat, or Mantle, or if he be diſpoſed, may nakedly hold forth the Truth. <hi>Kneel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> is not neceſſary becauſe a man
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:101809:41"/> may ſtand, or ſit, or loll, or ly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long. What then? Is it therefore unlawful for the Church to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine to ſome one of theſe? No ſure; for according to the latter Conception, when one extream is neceſſary to be embrac'd, the Church may reſolve which is beſt. And this is the Caſe here. For though no one of the two be neceſſary, yet ſome one of them all muſt be embrac'd. For the Sacrament cannot be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved but in ſome poſture or other, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I conceive therefore his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips latter Conception, in the very birth of it pulls the former by the heel and ſupplants it. For if the Church may reſolve which of the two extreams is beſt, where one is neceſſary; with as much reaſon may ſhe reſolve which of four or five is beſt, becauſe ſome one of them muſt be embrac'd. Or elſe it will follow, becauſe a Pulpit is not
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:101809:41"/> neceſſary, in as much as a man may preach in a Tub (at leaſt if it be ſet on a Treſſle) becauſe a Folio Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble is not neceſſary in as much as a man may read in a leſſer print; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe a Communion Cup of Silver is not neceſſary, there being other Metals; therefore the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Court</hi> may not compel a man to pay to the Church-Wardens rate, when he hath provided theſe things. And what a bleſſed Reformation will this be!</p>
            <p>And yet it ſeems there is danger leſt the powers already given ſhould be too large, wherefore he limits again. <hi>This power wherever it is muſt be very warily exerciſed, ſince of all two extreams</hi> (and according to<note place="margin">Idem ibid.</note> his Principles the Caſe will be the ſame, where four, or five, or twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty things are oppoſed) <hi>only one can be lawful, ſo that one is wholſome and the other poyſon.</hi> But where at laſt is this
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:101809:42"/> power? be it little or much, let us know its bounds. <hi>The Church hath a Judicative declarative power, like the Judges in</hi> Weſtminſter-Hall, <hi>but not a legiſlative power, as the</hi> King <hi>and</hi> Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament. If a man may be bold to ask again; Who is this Church? You ſhall find his <hi>Lordſhip</hi> give a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble anſwer. <hi>By the Church here I mean</hi> (ſays he) <hi>not only one, or two, or a few of what rank ſoever, but all, even every true Member of the whole Church; for I conceive every ſuch member hath</hi> de jure, <hi>a vote in this Determination.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A right Oecumenical Council indeed, when every member of the body muſt be conven'd to declare his opinion, about any Rite or Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony that ſhall happen to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led into queſtion. If I may add a Conception of my own, I ſhould think it worth enquiring, whether Women and Children be not true Members of the whole Church, the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:101809:42"/> liberty of whoſe Conſciences may be as little impoſed upon as that of us men. Well, to gratifie his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip we will ſuppoſe what is Impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to be put in practice: Every true Member of the whole Church, awaken'd and alarm'd with the ſcruples of <hi>John a Nokes,</hi> about the poſture in which the Sacrament is be received; is met together to declare and determine what is beſt to be done. Now, it ever the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains brought forth a Mouſe, you ſhall ſee how little this Convention ſignifies; for when every Calves- Head hath ſpoke an Oracle, every one paſſed their Vote, let us Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine that ſome one among them (and it is hardly poſſible it ſhould be otherwiſe) ſhould be diſſatisfied and diſſent from the Judgment of the greateſt part of the Church, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter reading and praying ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue to diſſent, <hi>In this caſe</hi> (he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives<note place="margin">Ibid.</note>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:101809:43"/> once more) <hi>no power on earth ought to force that mans practice more than his Judgment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Liberty! Oh ſweet Liberty! What pity it is the <hi>Lord Brooke</hi> hath not another life to loſe in defence of this Goſpel liberty. But ſeriouſly (ſo far as amazement will admit) are not things now brought to a ſtrange Concluſion? Will it not be perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in vain, to determine any thing at all about Church-Matters? For, even in thoſe things that ſeem <hi>Indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent,</hi> one is <hi>Best,</hi> the other <hi>Unlowful.</hi> When the Church hath reſolved which <hi>is beſt,</hi> yet every man muſt be left to do what he <hi>thinks beſt.</hi> So is the State of the Church as deplo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable as ever was that of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth<note place="margin">Judges 21.</note> of <hi>Iſrael. In thoſe dayes when there was no King in Iſrael, but every man did that which was right in his own Eyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are many other ſcurvy
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:101809:43"/> paſſages in that ill-natur'd Book, and many Unworthy Reflections upon my Lords the Biſhops that then were: but I muſt not digreſs to take notice of them. This proceſs of his is ſufficiently expoſed by this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of it.</p>
            <p>I confeſs I have met with two other Pamphlets that alſo demur in this thing. <hi>A Modeſt Diſcourſe concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Ceremonies,</hi> believes that the <hi>Churches Authority in commanding mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi>
               <note place="margin">Page 1.</note> 
               <hi>of Indifferency, wants ground from Scripture.</hi> And M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Bagſhaw</hi> in his <hi>Two great queſtions concerning things In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different in Religious Worſhip,</hi> holds it <hi>utterly unlawful for any Chriſtian Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate</hi>
               <note place="margin">Page 2.</note> 
               <hi>to impoſe the uſe of them.</hi> But neither of them are ſo extravagant, as to deny that there is any thing <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different,</hi> only they think what God hath not determin'd, men may not. Againſt whom I oppoſe to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</p>
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:101809:44"/>
            <p>Either Church-Governours have power in theſe Caſes to determine, or all people muſt be left to their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, to determine for themſelves. But what intolerable diſorder and confuſion would that bring into the Church? Then would God be the <hi>Author of confuſion</hi> and <hi>not of peace.</hi> There is then no power now left in the Church, that may take care that things be done <hi>decently</hi> and in <hi>order:</hi> but this is orderly and decent, that every man ſhould have liberty to break Order, and go his own way. And if in forms and modes of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip there could be as many differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences (as thoſe that are, are not few) as men, it might be lawful for every man to go by himſelf, and a ſingle perſon ſhould conſtitute a Church. Men would never agree neither about time, nor place of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Worſhip, nor about the perſon that ſhould teach them and pray for
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:101809:44"/> them, nor about the manner of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Prayers, or publick Preaching, nor about the form of adminiſtring the Sacraments, nor is it eaſy to name any one thing in the publick worſhip of God, wherein all men would be of one mind, but if all were left to their liberty when Church-Governours have deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min'd as they think moſt expedient; every private perſon ſhall have a Negative Vote, and if he like not to worſhip God in the ſame way as others do, he muſt paſs without controul to worſhip as he pleaſes, or if it ſo pleaſe him, not to worſhip at all.</p>
            <p>But theſe are but the <hi>Capricio</hi>'s of ſome few particular men, the vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of which I need not labour much to ſhew, becauſe however the Fox pronounces the Grapes ſowr which he cannot reach; however ſome diſcontented men quarrel at the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:101809:45"/> power of the Keys, when they do not hang at their own Girdle, yet there never was any body of men, that did at any time uſurp a power to make Laws, and determine in Church Affairs, but did proceed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this Principle, that it is lawful to make determinations in things <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different;</hi> and plain it is that the <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians</hi> and <hi>Independents</hi> both, allow what I now contend for.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Preſbyterians</hi> in the Preface<note place="margin">Sect. 9.</note> to their <hi>Directory,</hi> diſtinguiſh ſome things to be of Divine Inſtitution, and others not, and of theſe they ſay: <hi>Other things we have endeavoured to ſet forth according to the Rules of Christian prudence, agreeable to the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral rules of the word of God.</hi> Alſo in their <hi>Confeſſion of Faith</hi> ſet out with<note place="margin">Aſſemb. Conf. of Faith. Ch. 31.</note> their Catechiſms they define: <hi>That it belongs to Synods and Councils to ſet down rules and directions for better order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the publick worſhip of God and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:101809:45"/> of his Church, which Decrees and determinations if Conſonant to the word of God</hi> (where it is worthy ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving, that when they are eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing their own Authority and way, they expect not expreſs Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands for every thing they do, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they have been obſerved to huff at Epiſcopacy and to require Commands for our eſtabliſhments) <hi>are to be received with reverence and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, not only for their agreement with the word, but alſo for the power whereby they are made, as being an Ordinance of God appointed thereto in his word.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Since theſe firſt attempts of the <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> we find ſome writing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formably to their dictates and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing thus. <hi>We freely grant that the</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Diſcourſe Liturg.</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Chap.</hi> 16.</note> 
               <hi>Civil power, or the Church (orderly aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled) may determine at what hours on the Lords-day the Congregation ſhall meet, as alſo it ſhall determine particular times for Faſting or Thankſgiving, as Gods provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:101809:46"/> ſhall adminiſter Occaſions,</hi> (and yet ſome of this way are againſt keeping <hi>Chriſtmaſs,</hi> &amp;c.) <hi>that places of publick worſhip ſhall be erected, frequented, kept decent, and an</hi> Hundred <hi>things of that Nature, which even reaſon and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture it ſelf teaches all ſober perſons to be ſuch, as that without ſome Order to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in them, the worſhip of God either would not be performed, or would be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decently performed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>True it is that the ſame men ſay in the ſame <hi>Chapter, The Aſſertion of the Churches power in appointing Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies and Circumſtances of Divine Worſhip is the very root of all, the</hi> Pandora'<hi>s Box, the very Fountain head of all thoſe Impoſitions, which have bred ſo much trouble, diſturbance, and perſecutions in the Church of God.</hi> Which how to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile to what is juſt now quoted, I well know not, nor to another paſſage in the ſame <hi>Chapter,</hi> where though they deſire to diſtinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:101809:46"/> 
               <hi>Circumſtances</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies</hi> of worſhip, yet they acknowledge thus. <hi>That the word of God hath left many things (not poſſible to be determin'd by it) to the Authority of the Chriſtian Magiſtrate cannot be denied, whether any Ceremonies or no is a queſtion, divers Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances relating to the worſhip of God, are undoubtedly ſo left.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When I compare theſe things, I know not how to underſtand the Coherence of them, unleſs it be thus. When Church-Governours are <hi>Epiſcopal,</hi> and ſhall aſſume a pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to appoint Ceremonies and Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of divine worſhip, this is the <hi>fountain head of Impoſitions that breed disturbance and perſecutions:</hi> But if they ſhall chance to be <hi>Preſbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> then there are an <hi>Hundred things not determin'd by the word of God,</hi> but left to their Chriſtian Prudence. For Example: A Convocation may not by a <hi>Canon</hi> or <hi>Rubrick</hi> appoint, <hi>a font
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:101809:47"/> of ſtone</hi> at the Weſt end of the Church, nor <hi>kneeling</hi> at the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, nor that the Bread and Wine be ſeverally diſtributed to every Communicant, but the <hi>Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory</hi> may make appointments con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to all theſe and an <hi>hundred</hi> things of the like nature. For the Ordinance of <hi>Parliament</hi> (all the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority it had) which eſtabliſhed the <hi>Directory,</hi> ſays. <hi>The Directory for pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick worſhip herein ſet forth, ſhall hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth be uſed, purſued, and obſerved, in all exerciſes of the publick worſhip of God, in every Congregation, Church, Chappel, and place of publick Worſhip, within this Kingdom of</hi> England, <hi>and Dominion of</hi> Wales.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Independents</hi> in their <hi>Confeſſion of Faith,</hi> ſet out from the <hi>Savoy,</hi> 1658. ſpeak to the ſame purpoſe. <hi>There</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 1. Sect. 6.</note> 
               <hi>are ſome Circumstances concerning the worſhip of God and Government of the Church, common to Humane Actions and
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:101809:47"/> Societies, which are to be Ordered by the light of Nature, and Chriſtian prudence, according to the General Rules of the word, which are always to be obſerved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now I muſt crave leave that our Adverſaries would judge whether they are not unequal to us, in deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us a liberty which they grant to themſelves. In this general Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of things, it is not mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial to ask for what reaſon they ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple our Ceremonies, whether as ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificant or popiſh, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which ſhall be examined in due time. All that I now conclude, is no more than what they themſelves believe and practiſe, <hi>viz.</hi> It is no <hi>ſuperstitious Opinion</hi> to believe that the Church may make Determinations in things <hi>Indifferent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>4. <hi>Where the Governours of the Church</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sect. 10.</note> 
               <hi>have power to determine, it can be no ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious opinion to believe, they ought to be obeyed, in the exerciſe of this their law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:101809:48"/> power.</hi> Yea, if it ſhould be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted (what I do not by any means grant, only to come as cloſe as may be to our Adverſaries, I ſuppoſe the caſe) that it is not well done to Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ſuch things <hi>Indifferent;</hi> yet if they be not in their own nature evil, it is better to obey than to diſturb the peace of the Church, and to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate from eſtabliſhed order. <hi>Zan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy</hi> and <hi>Calvin</hi> are profeſſedly our Advocates in this Matter, on whoſe Teſtimony I build the more, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are of great Authority with thoſe who diſſent from us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Zanchy</hi> wrote a Letter to Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> wherein he did earneſtly perſwade her not to Impoſe the <hi>Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plice</hi> and ſuch like things upon the Clergy of <hi>England.</hi> This he did with<note place="margin">Zanch E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtol. lib. 1. p. 111. Tom. ult.</note> great Zeal, and it may ſeem with ſome acrimony; as if he had been a great Patron of <hi>Non-Conformity,</hi> and I will not deny that it ſeems by that
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:101809:48"/> Letter he did greatly diſlike ſuch Impoſitions; and but that he was commanded by his Prince to write as he did (he did <hi>Coactus ſcribere</hi> as he profeſſes) it is a Letter that might argue him to meddle too much in the affairs of another Church: but we take it as we find it, and not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all that is there ſaid, it is manifeſt that <hi>Zanchy</hi> was of our ſide.</p>
            <p>That he was abuſed in the Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation that was given him of our affairs, appears by his Letter to the <hi>Queen,</hi> wherein he complains of her introducing and eſtabliſhing all the Maſſing attire of the Romiſh Prieſts, for ſo he calls them. <hi>Veſtes albas ac lineas, quibus in papatu utuntur ſacrifici: Antichriſti ſupellectilem: Papistarum Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piam pompam: Idololarriae &amp; ſuperſtitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis Papiſticae reliquias vel ſaltem ſymbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la:</hi> that is in the Engliſh of ſome of our Malecontents, All the <hi>rags</hi> of the
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:101809:49"/> 
               <hi>whore of</hi> Babylon. Whereas the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire of their Prieſts is made up of ſix Veſtments (as a Learned man of our own hath obſerved out of their <hi>Ritualists) Amictus, Alba, Cingulum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Falkner</hi> Libert. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſt. lib. 2. Cap. 4. §. 9.</note> 
               <hi>Stola, Manipulus, Capſula,</hi> all far dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent from the <hi>Surplice;</hi> and theſe <hi>ſix Garments are accounted holy Garments uſed by their Priests, and all of them have their particular Conſecrations, as the Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plice in the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>hath not. Zanchy</hi> then thus miſtaking the caſe was more eager than he needed to have been, but he was under ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and greater miſtake.</p>
            <p>It was reported to him that there was great danger, leſt many pious men ſhould be turn'd out of their Livings upon this Occaſion; yea, it was told him, that there were <hi>ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Epiſcopi</hi> (that muſt be ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable number of the Twenty ſix that are in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales) Viri omni eruditione &amp; pietate inſignes, qui
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:101809:49"/> malint Officio &amp; loco cedere quam iſtiuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modi vestes admittere.</hi> There were many Biſhops that would not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form. Now who that knows any thing of the State of the <hi>Church of England, Anno</hi> 1571. (when that Letter was written) knows not that the Biſhops of that time were ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently ſatisfied with the Conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that was then urged, nor was there one among them (for ſo far as I can now find) that made ſo much noiſe about theſe things as Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <hi>Hooper</hi> of <hi>Gloceſter</hi> did under <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth: If therefore <hi>Zan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy</hi> may be excuſed for endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what he could in favour of thoſe good and Learned men whoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>auctoration he fear'd; yet that not being the caſe, the earneſtneſs of his Letter (if we ſhould yield more to his judgment than of neceſſity we are obliged to do) will not ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nify much to the reproach of our Conformity.</p>
            <pb n="76" facs="tcp:101809:50"/>
            <p>But we have greater aſſurance that <hi>Zanchy</hi> was our Friend: For when he had dated his Letter to the <hi>Queen</hi> from <hi>Heidelberg, Sept.</hi> 10. 1571. he dates another the very next day<note place="margin">Zanch. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. lib. 2. p. 181. Tom. ult.</note> to Biſhop <hi>Juell</hi> (though it be doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful whether he lived to receive it, becauſe he died the <hi>23d</hi> of the ſame Month) from the tenor of which I conclude, that in his Letter to the <hi>Queen</hi> he ſays nothing to prove the uſages of our Church unlawful to be practiſ'd, (whatever his opinion might be of the conveniency of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing them) or if he did, he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſays it again the very next day in his Letter to the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> which of ſo Learned and fix'd a man, is not ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily to be believed. For the very occaſion of that ſecond Letter, was to deſire Biſhop <hi>Juell</hi> and other Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, to uſe their Authority with the reſt to perſwade. <hi>Ne ſi Regina amoveri nullo modo poſſit à ſententiâ, ipſi
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:101809:50"/> propterea ſuas deſerere malint ſtationes, quam edicto Regio obtemperare.</hi> If the Queen were reſolv'd and would be obey'd, he would have all the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy <hi>rather obey than leave their places and Employments.</hi> He goes on declare his Opinion, that for ſuch things as theſe, Miniſters may not leave their Flocks: He acknowledges the Caſe, that where things are in their own nature evil, we muſt with the Apoſtles <hi>obey God rather than Man,</hi> and then adds, <hi>Si vero res ſuâ naturâ adia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorae, lege mandato<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> regio praecipiantur, quando alterutrum neceſſe ſit, ut aut ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datur loco, aut tali mandato obtemperetur, obtemperandum potius eſſe,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>When the Magiſtrates command Indifferent things upon this neceſſity, that men muſt obey or forſake their Miniſtry, they must rather obey.</hi> Nay he reckons this Caſe ſo clear, that he concludes: <hi>Eſſe vero hanc ſententiam it a certam &amp; perſpicuam, tum in ſacris literis tum apud
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:101809:51"/> patres &amp; in Hiſtoriis Eccleſiaſticis, ut ſupervacaneum omnino ſit, ullam adferre probationem apud illos, qui vel mediocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in ſcripturis ſunt exercitati. Nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam enim propter res ſuâ naturâ adiapho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, deſerenda est vocatio legitima &amp; neceſſaria. They who ever conſulted the Scriptures, or Fathers, or Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtorians, will need no proof of this, That it can never be lawful for men to leave a neceſſary Employment</hi> (ſuch as that of the Miniſtry is) <hi>for the ſake of Indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Rites.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If this will not convert a <hi>Non-Conformiſt,</hi> yet I hope it will make them aſham'd to quote <hi>Zanchy</hi>'s Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the <hi>Queen,</hi> as if it were much to our diſadvantage (as the <hi>Replyer</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vid. Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges <hi>Anſwer Rejoin'd.</hi> Chap. 1. Sect. 19.</note> upon Biſhop <hi>Mortons</hi> defence does) let both his Letters be compar'd, and much good may they do them.</p>
            <p>That this was <hi>Zanchy</hi>'s ſetled Judgment, appears from what he
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:101809:51"/> elſewhere ſays, in defence of Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments peculiar to Divine Service: <hi>Quod veteres Epiſcopi coenam adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turi,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zanc. Tom. 4. de Cultu Dei exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no lib. 1. Cap. 16.</note> 
               <hi>aliam induerint veſtem, ad mutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem coenae nihil pertinet. Non enim Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus juſſit, ut communibus veſtibus induti coenam adminiſtraremus, ſicut &amp; ipſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dutus erat, ſed tantum ut faceremus quod &amp; ipſe fecit. Idem de multis aliis rebus dici poteſt, tam in Baptiſmo quam in coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nâ Dominicâ.</hi> Whereas the <hi>Biſhops of old did celebrate the Euchariſt in a pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar Garment, this makes no change in that ſervice, for our Lord Chriſt did not command us to be clothed as he was, but to do what he did.</hi> And the ſame may be ſaid of many other things, both in Baptiſm and the Lords Supper.</p>
            <p>The ſum of all he thus expreſſes, <hi>Quae addita ſunt, ſed tanquam adiaphora, propter ordinem, propter decorum, &amp; ad aedificationem, ea ſubſtantiam Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum eo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> cultum non mutarunt. Thoſe things that are added for Order, Decency,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:101809:52"/> and Edification, make no alteration in the ſubſtance of the Sacraments, or of Divine Worſhip.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I conclude then, though we yield <hi>Zanchy</hi> theirs, as to his Opinion, that it is not well done to impoſe theſe <hi>Indifferent</hi> things, yet he is clearly ours as to the Propoſition I main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain. When <hi>Indifferent</hi> things are once determin'd (whatever Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours may have to anſwer for ſuch Impoſitions) becauſe they are not in their own nature evil, it is better to obey than to diſturb the peace of the Church.</p>
            <p>But M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Calvin</hi> is a greater man<note place="margin">Sect. 11.</note> than D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Zanchy,</hi> and the cauſe which he condemns ſhall ly under a great prejudice: his opinion therefore<note place="margin">
                  <hi>M. Durell</hi> View of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and publick worſhip in the Reform. Churches beyond the Seas, <hi>pag: 161. &amp;c.</hi>
               </note> muſt be conſider'd. However he be generally eſteemed no great friend to Epiſcopacy, yet M. <hi>Durell</hi> hath endeavour'd to vindicate him from being very Antiepiſpocal<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Be that as
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:101809:52"/> it will; if our <hi>N. Cts</hi> will ſtand or fall to <hi>Calvins</hi> Judgment, our advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage is as great as we need deſire.</p>
            <p>1. For firſt he does greatly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire ſet forms of Prayer. So he ſays in a Letter to the <hi>Protector</hi> of <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth. <hi>Quod ad formulam precum &amp;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Calv. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. 87. Dat. 1548.</note> 
               <hi>Rituum Eccleſiaſticorum, valde probo, ut certa illa extet à quâ Paſtoribus diſcedere in ſuâ functione non liceat. I do greatly like that forms of Prayer, and the Rites of the Church ſhould be ſtated, ſo as Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters in the exerciſe of their function ſhould not have leave to vary from them.</hi> His reaſons are Three, <hi>Ut conſulatur quorundam ſimplicitati &amp; Imperitiae: Ut certius conſtet omnium Eccleſiarum inter ſe conſenſus. Postremo ut obviam eatur deſultoriae quorundam levitati qui novatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes quaſdam affectant. Firſt, For the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply of ſome mens inabilities</hi> (a reaſon that our modern N. C<hi rend="sup">ts</hi>. in this time of Goſpel light, think an underva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luing of them) <hi>Secondly, That the
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:101809:53"/> ſeveral Churches</hi> (of the ſame Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion) <hi>may appear to conſent together. Thirdly, For a ſecurity againſt Innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors</hi> (and in that alſo I wiſh they were not concern'd.) Upon this laſt reaſon <hi>Calvin</hi> adds, that there ſhould be <hi>ſumma quaedam doctrinae ab omnibus recepta, quam inter praedicandum ſequan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur omnes, ad quam etiam obſervandam omnes Epiſcopi &amp; Parochi jurejurando ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtringantur, ut nemo ad munus Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum admittatur, niſi ſpondeat ſibi illum ſenſum inviolatum futurum. Extet prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terea communis Catechiſmi formula,</hi> &amp;c. Which I thus accommodate to our Uſage, he could not think it unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>to ſubſcribe to the thirty nine Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. Becauſe ſome Ceremonies muſt accompany Divine Service, it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by the former words that he would have them ſtated too. I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal not his Opinion, that he would have but few Ceremonies for fear of
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:101809:53"/> 
               <hi>Superſtition. Nihil conſultius video</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epiſt. 303. Dat. 1560.</note> 
               <hi>quam parciſſimis Ceremoniis uti in Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiâ, ſatis enim Experientiâ conſtat, quàm proclivis ſit lapſus in ſuperſtitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if any ſhall hence infer, that <hi>Calvin,</hi> if he were alive, would judge us to abound in ſuperfluous Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, I oppoſe his former Letter to the <hi>Protector,</hi> where he ſpeaks, <hi>de abolendis &amp; radicitus evellendis abuſibus &amp; corruptelis,</hi> of <hi>rooting out abuſes:</hi> but he inſtances but in three things, <hi>Praying for the dead, Chriſm</hi> and <hi>extream Unction.</hi> All which having now no place in our Church, and it being undeniable that we are reformed to ſome greater degrees than in <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixths time, we have fair reaſon to ſay that the preſent ſtate of things is ſuch as <hi>Calvin</hi> would not diſallow; at moſt if he would have adviſed to have omitted ſome of our Ceremonies, yet in the ſame
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:101809:54"/> place where he deſires Ceremonies ſhould be few, he adds, <hi>Aliud vero eſt, cum nobis jus non eſt admittendi aut re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudiandi quod videbitur. Si non licet ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinere quod cupimus, feramus iſtos defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus, non approbemus. Where we are to obey and not to rule, let us bear with thoſe defects which we need not approve.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. But <hi>Calvin</hi> is the man, who called ſome of our Rites <hi>Fooleries.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe our N. C<hi rend="sup">ts</hi>. ſhall have liberty to make the moſt of that word, I ſo tranſlate it, though others think it may be rendred <hi>Unfitneſſes.</hi> Let them take the advantage of it, provided they will acknowledge that at the ſame time he calls them <hi>tolerable.</hi> The words are in a Letter to ſome Engliſh Divines at <hi>Frankford,</hi> in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> time. <hi>In Anglicanâ</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ep. 200. Dat. 1555.</note> 
               <hi>Liturgiâ qualem deſcribitis, multas video fuiſſe tolerabiles Ineptias. Calvin</hi> being at a diſtance, takes things as they were repreſented to him, therefore
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:101809:54"/> he ſpeaks of the <hi>Engliſh Liturgy</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the deſcription they gave of it, and there is ſome reaſon to ſuſpect, that they who gave him that account, miſrepreſented the caſe. I am not alone in the Imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. M. <hi>Durell</hi> is before me who<note place="margin">View of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, <hi>&amp;c. p. 117.</hi>
               </note> undertakes it at large. But <hi>Calvin</hi> ſays moreover <hi>video fuiſſe:</hi> ſo it had been (he thought) in <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixths time, and who knows not what perfective alterations have been ſince made? Suppoſe at moſt he did not like ſome things, yet this is certain, that he did not think it worth while to contend about them, for ſo he ſays in the ſame Letter. <hi>In</hi>
               <note place="margin">Id. ibid.</note> 
               <hi>rebus mediis ut ſunt externi Ritus, facilem me &amp; flexibilem praebeo. In ſuch Indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent matters as outward Rites are, I am an eaſy man and ready to be perſwaded.</hi> And I give but Two Inſtances more that I may have done with him.</p>
            <p>When he writes to <hi>Bullinger</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:101809:55"/> Biſhop <hi>Hooper</hi>'s Scruples and troubles, he ſays, <hi>De pileo &amp; veſte</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ep. 120. Dat. 1551.</note> 
               <hi>lineâ maluiſſem (ut illa etiam non probem) non uſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> adeo ipſum pugnare, id<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> etiam nuper ſuadebam.</hi> Though <hi>I do not much like the Square-Cap, and Surplice, yet I wiſh</hi> Hooper <hi>had not been ſo fierce a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, and ſo I lately perſwaded him.</hi> Yea, in an affair of their own, <hi>Beza</hi> reports him to have been of the ſame temper. Some there were at <hi>Geneva</hi> who had upon ſome pretences in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduc'd the uſe of <hi>Unleaven'd Bread</hi> (and of that only) at the <hi>Communion:</hi> At this others were ſo offended, that they inclin'd, rather to ſtay away than Communicate. <hi>Calvin</hi> who<note place="margin">Bez. Vit. Calvini. An. 1538.</note> was then withdrawn from <hi>Geneva,</hi> hearing of it, adviſed them, <hi>ne ob iſtud <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> litem moverent, ſic obti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuit panis Azymi uſus, de quo etiàm poſtea reſtitutus</hi> Calvinus <hi>nunquam contenden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum putavit, minimè tamen diſſimulans quid alioqui eſſet magis probaturus. He
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:101809:55"/> would not have them quarrel about ſuch an Indifferent matter. So the uſe of Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaven'd Bread was eſtabliſhed, which when</hi> Calvin <hi>return'd again, he did not think fit to make any diſturbance about, though he did not diſſemble that he rather wiſhed, it had been otherwiſe.</hi> It ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears then <hi>Calvin</hi> was not ſo inflexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in all matters of Conformity as many of our Modern N. C<hi rend="sup">ts</hi>. are.</p>
            <p>To <hi>Calvin</hi> and <hi>Zanchy</hi> it is eaſy to<note place="margin">Sect. 12. M. Durell <hi>View of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> &amp;c. p. 119. &amp; deinceps.</note> add like Teſtimonies out of other Authors magnified by the N. C<hi rend="sup">ts</hi>. M. <hi>Durell</hi> hath brought about forty, moſtly Divines, as it were into Council, delivering their Opinions about Ceremonies and Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of worſhip. All unanimouſly agreeing againſt our preſent Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, that theſe things, <hi>viz. the Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plice and Croſs, &amp;c.</hi> are not ſuch, for which a ſeparation is to be made: and if all do not ſpeak to every par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular matter in Controverſy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:101809:56"/> us, yet all ſpeak to ſome, and ſome to all, by all which it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, that the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> is not condemned by the <hi>Reformed Churches</hi> beyond the Seas, nay ſhe is juſtified, nay ſhe is admired.</p>
            <p>For the particular purpoſe of the Argument now in hand, I offer a few of our own Countrymen, and I cannot begin better than with <hi>T. Cartwright,</hi> who is quoted as <hi>profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Burges</hi> Preface to Anſw. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>join'd, <hi>p. 3, 4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>to oppoſe our Ceremonies as inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent but not as unlawful, and therefore perſwaded Miniſters, rather to wear the Garments than ceaſe their Miniſtry, and taught men to receive the Sacrament kneel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, if they could not have it otherwiſe, becauſe though the geſture be (as he takes it) incommodious, yet he ſays it is not ſimply unlawful.</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Sprint,</hi> alſo aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures us, <hi>that</hi> D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Humfrey,</hi> D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nolds,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Caſſand. Anglic. p. 163.</note> D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Sparks,</hi> D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Chaloner,</hi> D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Ay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ray,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Chaderton,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Knewſtubs,</hi> though they <hi>ſtood out and teſtified their
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:101809:56"/> diſlike againſt ſundry of the Ceremonies eſtabliſhed, yet they did in caſe of depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation yield to them, and ſtudiouſly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded others in this caſe to this pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of latter days M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Baxter</hi> hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termin'd, that <hi>it may be very ſinful to command ſome Ceremonies, when yet it may be the ſubjects duty to uſe them when they are commanded.</hi> Upon which Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition he ſays farther: <hi>If a thing</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Baxt.</hi> Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putat. of Church Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, <hi>p. 460.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>be ſimply unlawful, as being forbid by God himſelf, there no command of man can make it lawful: But if it be but incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient, or evil only by accident, or cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance, it is poſſible for the command of Governours to take off that accidental evil, and make it become a duty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have dwelt at large upon theſe Teſtimonies, not becauſe the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the thing is doubtful, ſo as to need ſuch a Confirmation, nor becauſe if it were, other Teſtimonies as conſiderable could not be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:101809:57"/> but to comply with the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor of the N. C<hi rend="sup">ts</hi>. and to deal with them at their own Weapon. They have made a great noiſe about the conſent of the <hi>Reformed Churches,</hi> and did <hi>Covenant to endeavour a Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on according to the Example of the beſt Reformed Churches;</hi> as if all that go under the name of the Reformed Churches beyond the Seas, did as much believe us <hi>Superſtitious</hi> as theſe men pretend to believe. Whereas beſide the Veneration which <hi>Span<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemius</hi> expreſſes to have for the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der<note place="margin">Epiſt. ad tertiam partem. Dub. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangel. An. 1638.</note> of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> in a time when Conformity went higher than of late days: beſides <hi>Bogerman's</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment at <hi>Dort</hi> to the <hi>Biſhop of Landaffe</hi> that then was, <hi>Domine, nos</hi>
               <note place="margin">Biſhop <hi>Hall</hi> Epiſcopacy by Divine Right, <hi>Sec. 4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>non ſumus adeo foelices,</hi> It was their misfortune not to be under Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Government; we have many more clear evidences of the great reſpect which Foreigners bear to the <hi>Church of England.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="91" facs="tcp:101809:57"/>
            <p>I conclude this Propoſition with the grave and excellent determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> in which he gives account of St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> too. <hi>Monica</hi> coming to <hi>Milan,</hi> and obſerving the Order of the Church there, that they did not faſt on <hi>Saturday</hi> as was uſual in other Churches, was trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled about it; for her ſatisfaction St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> adviſes with St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> who anſwers him, and reſolves her, by his own practice. <hi>Cum Romam</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſtin. Januario.</note> 
               <hi>venio, jejuno Sabbato, cum hîc ſum non jejuno; ſic etiam tu ad quam forte Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiam veneris, ejus morem ſerva, ſi cui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam non vis eſſe ſcandalo, nec quenquam tibi. When I am at</hi> Rome, <hi>I faſt on</hi> Saturday <hi>as they do there, here I do not; ſo I would have you, whereſoever you come, obſerve the Order of the place, if you would neither give nor take offence.</hi> An An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer which ſatisfied <hi>Monica,</hi> and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for an <hi>Oracle</hi> with St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> who adds of his own in the ſame Epiſtle:
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:101809:58"/> Some things Univerſal tradition had ſo confirmed, that he did not think fit they ſhould be alter'd, as the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of <hi>Eaſter</hi> and <hi>Whitſuntide, &amp;c.</hi> but then, <hi>Alia quae per loca terra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum</hi>
               <note place="margin">Id. ibid.</note> 
               <hi>variantur, ſicut eſt quod alii jeju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Sabbato, alii non, alii quotidie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municant, alii certis diebus,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>&amp; ſi quid aliud hujuſmodi animadverti poteſt, Totum hoc genus rerum liberas habet ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervationes, nec diſciplina ulla alia eſt in his melior, gravi prudenti<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Chriſtiano, quam ut eo modo agat, quo agere viderit Eccleſiam ad quamcun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> forte devenerit; quod enimne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> contra fidemne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> contra bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos mores injungitur,</hi> Indifferenter <hi>est habendum, &amp; pro eorum inter quos vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitur ſocietate ſervandum eſt.</hi> As to thoſe Obſervances which are divers in divers Countries, <hi>that ſome fast on</hi> Saturday, <hi>others not; ſome communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate every day, others at stated times: All ſuch things as theſe are free, and a grave and prudent Chriſtian can follow no
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:101809:58"/> better rule, than to behave himſelf ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Order of the Church, to which he ſhall chance to come: For what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is enjoin'd that is not againſt Faith, nor good manners, is to be eſteemed</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different, <hi>and to be practiſed according to the Company with which we converſe.</hi> St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> does rightly ſtate the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a thing <hi>Indifferent</hi> (ſuppoſe the <hi>Surplice</hi>) ſomewhat in its own nature not neceſſary, therefore in a Church that does not enjoin it, it may be omitted, ſomewhat in its own nature not Unlawful, therefore in a Church that does enjoin it, it ought to be uſed.</p>
            <p>5. <hi>It is no Superstitious Opinion to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sect. 13.</hi> Diſcourſe of Liturgies, <hi>Chap. 16. §. 9.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>that the Church may appoint ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant Ceremonies.</hi> This is another mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter wherein the N. C<hi rend="sup">ts</hi>. ſpeak big. <hi>It is not true that they have any Authority to appoint ſignificative Ceremonies, where are ſenſible ſigns to affect the Underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, this is to give them Authority to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:101809:59"/> Sacraments.</hi> Another formerly. <hi>All humane Ceremonies being appropriate</hi>
               <note place="margin">Abridg. <hi>Lincoln.</hi> See <hi>Burges</hi> Anſwer Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>join'd. <hi>Chap. 3. Sect. 1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>to Gods ſervice, if they be ordain'd to teach any ſpiritual duty by their Myſtical ſignification, are unlawful. But ſuch are theſe Three, the</hi> Surplice, <hi>the</hi> Croſs <hi>in</hi> Baptiſm, <hi>and</hi> Kneeling <hi>in receiving the Communion.</hi> Ergo, <hi>they are Unlawful.</hi> There is a clear difference between ſigns of Grace inwardly infus'd, and ſigns of duty enjoin'd. It is the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of a Sacrament to be an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſign of inward Grace. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore becauſe Chriſt is the Author of Grace, as it belongs to him whoſe the deed of Gift is to ſet to his Seal, ſo is it the Prerogative of our Lord Chriſt to inſtitute Sacraments for his Church. But ſigns of duty are other things, and this diſtinction is thus expreſſed by the Learned <hi>Morton. There be two acceptions of the word My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> Burges ut ſupra. Chap. 3. Sec. 4.</note> 
               <hi>one Sacramental by ſignification of Grace confer'd by God, the other only mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:101809:59"/> ſignifying ſome duty of men to God. The Myſtical Ceremonies condemned by Learned Writers, are Sacramental; all the Ceremonies which we defend, are My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical, Moral, not Sacramental.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They who have written of theſe things, have given us divers Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, both out of the Old Teſtament and New, where inſignificant Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies have been allowably pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed, although they have not been ſtrictly Sacramental, nor of Divine Inſtitution. That which I offer to conſideration, is ſomewhat not fully retorted upon our Adverſaries, that I have any where obſerved, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I take liberty to inlarge upon it, when I have firſt mov'd one queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Put the Caſe a <hi>Canon</hi> or Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of our <hi>Church,</hi> ſhould enjoin the Sexton to make his Graves Eaſt and Weſt, and to take care that they who are buried be laid with their Feet to the Eaſt. I ask, would it be
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:101809:60"/> lawful, or unlawful, to obey this Conſtitution? Unlawful? How can that be ſo, when it is commanded, which is now generally practiſed, and that without ſcruple? If lawful, then is a ſignificant Ceremony al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed lawful, for though all men may not think of it, or may not ſo deſign, yet there can be no doubt but the Original of that Cuſtom, had a Reſpect to the Reſurrection of the Body, and to an expectation of Chriſts coming to Judgment, the belief of which was declar'd by this ſignificant Ceremony.</p>
            <p>But that which I urge is this. They againſt whom we argue, contend for <hi>ſitting</hi> at the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, and that for this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, becauſe it is a <hi>ſignificant poſture.</hi> That it is any where in the <hi>New-Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament</hi> commanded to receive the Sacrament <hi>ſitting,</hi> no man in his Wits will ſay: Yet the <hi>Presbyterians</hi>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:101809:60"/> have often argued for it, upon the account of its ſignificancy. So I have heard it out of the Pulpit. <hi>That geſture which ought to be kept above all the reſt, is Sitting, becauſe though it be but a Circumſtance, yet it hath ſome ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificancy in it, becauſe it is a ſupper ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture. And ſecondly and chiefly, becauſe it ſignifies the familiarity that is between Chriſt and Believers,</hi> Luke 22. 30. <hi>This Supper is a Type of the Everlaſting Supper in Heaven, where one ſhall not ſit and another ſtand.</hi> I name not my Author becauſe he is long ſince dead, but I am certain I do him no wrong. And to make it appear that this is their Doctrine, I add a Printed Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony.</p>
            <p>Among the Treatiſes that bear M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Bradſhaws</hi> name, one is a <hi>Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition concerning Kneeling at the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> wherein are theſe words. <hi>Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bradſh.</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes. <hi>p. 104.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>the end of a Sacrament, is to inform the outward man, by ſenſible demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:101809:61"/> it pleaſed our Maſter to uſe ſuch a geſture, as agreeably with Bread and Wine, ſetteth out our Communion and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual familiarity with him, and rejoicing in him, and therefore as he ſays, If any man hear my voice,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>I will come in to him and ſup with him, and he with me: So he ſays, Many ſhall come from the Eaſt and Weſt, and ſhall ſit with</hi> Abraham, &amp;c. <hi>By which place it appears, that as by Supper, ſo by ſitting, familiar rejoice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or rejoicing familiarity is expreſſed. Therefore not kneeling but ſitting is for receiving.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is plain then, that <hi>ſitting</hi> is reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on'd a <hi>ſignificant poſture.</hi> It is alſo plain, that it is required in the <hi>Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Direc. Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebra. Commun.</note> 
               <hi>The Table being decently covered, and ſo conveniently plac'd, that the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municants may orderly ſit about it, or at it,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>I know the pretence is, that they do not Inſtitute a ſignificant Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, they only retain it, as having
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:101809:61"/> warrant from the Example of our Saviour. So ſays the foremention'd Propoſition. <hi>Kneeling is contrary to</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
               <hi>the Example of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, who miniſtred and receiv'd ſitting, or in ſuch a geſture as in thoſe Countreys was most uſed at eating, from which Example to differ without warrant from Gods word, cannot be without fault, ſeeing the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of holy men, much more that of Chriſt, are to be followed except there be ſome reaſonable cauſe to the contrary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In Anſwer to which I oppoſe three things.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First, If the Example of Chriſt were as they ſay, yet it does no more conclude for our ſitting, than for our receiving at Supper time,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly, They have not the Example of Chriſt, for that manner of ſitting which they now urge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly, It is not abſolutely certain, whether they have his Example for any manner of ſitting at all.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="100" facs="tcp:101809:62"/>
            <p>1. Suppoſe the moſt, that the<note place="margin">Sect. 14.</note> Apoſtles at the firſt Inſtitution of the Sacrament, did receive it <hi>ſitting,</hi> where is the Argument, becauſe they did, therefore ſo muſt we? Let this be proved. Where is the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Command that makes it our duty to follow this Example? <hi>Cedo locum</hi> and we yield. That muſt not be ſaid. What then? Will they ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue from the Equity of the Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple? Let us go on then and ſay, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the ſame Example we muſt receive at night, in an upper room, and only Males: For either the whole Example binds in all Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, or in none; or ſome differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence muſt be aſſign'd between this Circumſtance and the other of Time and place, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And what I pray ſhall that be? Is it becauſe (which is a ſufficient reaſon) they were but Occaſional? there was no deſign in Inſtituting and adminiſtring the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:101809:62"/> in ſuch a place, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was judg'd by our Bleſſed Saviour a convenient place; Or at night, but becauſe the Paſs-over was firſt to be eaten, and that night our Bleſſed Saviour was to be betrayed, therefore that time of night was moſt proper, becauſe it could not be ſooner or later. Now let it be conſider'd, was it not alſo Occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, that they receiv'd it <hi>ſitting?</hi> ſo as their Maſter found them at the Paſs-over (as is now ſuppos'd) ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in haſt, he adminiſters this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament. Why therefore ſhould this come into Example rather than the other Circumſtances, unleſs (which can never be proved) there be ſome indications in the Goſpel, that it was the pleaſure of our Lord that this part of his Example ſhould oblige and not the reſt.</p>
            <p>Oh! but this geſture ſignifies (as was before ſaid) and does it ſo? Who
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:101809:63"/> can tell that? Who may be bold to ſay, that the poſture which was uſed upon occaſion, was intended for ſignification, when no ſuch thing is ſaid, only the wits of men have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed this reaſon, and imagin'd a ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificancy in it? But be it ſo. May not then alſo ſome ſignification be faſten'd upon the time and place? It is beſt to receive in an upper room: this ſignifies the exalted ſtate to which Believers are receiv'd, and by which they are dignified, whereby alſo they are rais'd up to a nearneſs to Heaven in that holy Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance. Again, it is beſt to receive at night: this ſignifies, after a poor Sinner hath been wearied in his days of ſin, as men at night turn to their reſt after the labours of the day; ſo now after the labours of ſin, <hi>Return to thy reſt, O my Soul, for the Lord hath dealt bountifully with thee,</hi> Pſal. 116. and <hi>Come unto me all ye that labour,</hi> &amp;c.
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:101809:63"/> 
               <hi>and I will give you reſt,</hi> Math. 11. I dare ſay as good Texts to prove re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving at night, as <hi>ſitting</hi> with <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> in the Kingdom of God proves the poſture. Thus is it eaſy to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe and imagine; and if this ſhall be thought a worſhipping God after our own devices (as the men who ſeem ſo much to abhor <hi>Superstition</hi> will be ready to ſay) I ſee not but they who contend ſo much for ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, will be guilty, unleſs they can make it appear that the Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture hath rather recommended one than another. Now if I ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat thoſe Tragical Declamations againſt <hi>adding to the word of God, Will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worſhip,</hi> and <hi>mens devices in the worſhip of God,</hi> of which their writings are full; how would they all fit here? For what is, if this be not worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping God after mens Imaginations, when they will make differences where our Bleſſed Saviour hath
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:101809:64"/> made none? And yet this is the beſt that can be ſaid of this Caſe: for this ſuppoſes that Chriſts Example recommends ſitting.</p>
            <p>2. Whereas this is farther to be ſaid, They have not ſo much as Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple for that manner of ſitting which they now urge: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Matth. 26. Luke 22.</note> the two words uſed by the <hi>Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts</hi> upon this occaſion, do not ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie ſuch a ſitting as is now in uſe: It is therefore generally agreed, that their poſture was more like to lying than ſitting. So that the beſt of their Argument can be but thus: Becauſe our Bleſſed Saviour gave the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to his Diſciples in that geſture which they uſed at Meals, which was a kind of lying, therefore we ought to receive it in the geſture now uſed at Meals which is ſitting: where we muſt deſire their Logick to tell us, what degree of neceſſity is in this ſequele, becauſe they did
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:101809:64"/> one thing, we muſt do another. Yet neither is this the worſt of it, all this is but a ſuppoſition of that which they are never able to prove. For</p>
            <p>3. It is not abſolutely certain, in what poſture they did then receive the Lords Supper. Probably they continued in the ſame poſture, but who can peremptorily conclude it? Who can demonſtrate to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, but that when our Bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, while they were eating, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly betook himſelf to the Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of a new Sacrament, they to addreſs themſelves to a new ſervice, might betake themſelves to a new geſture? I cannot prove they did, nor (for ought I can find) can any body prove they did not. There is nothing concluſive in any of the Evangeliſts, that they did certainly continue in the ſame poſture; Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs the Order of St. <hi>Luke</hi> be inſiſted
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:101809:65"/> on, who (<hi>Chap.</hi> 22.) after the Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of the Sacrament hath theſe words, <hi>But behold the hand of him that betrays me is with me at the Table.</hi> Which Order ſignifies little to thoſe who will not yield <hi>Judas</hi> to have been at the Sacrament (as divers of our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries will not) but admit he was there, as ſeems very probable, yet though they were all at the ſame ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble as before (and who can demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate but it might be another table) yet it does not appear certain, that they were in the ſame poſture as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. This doubt I move, not as a thing in it ſelf conſiderable, but to repreſent how ſtrongly ſome men (and even the ſame who call ſo much for Scripture grounds, and for a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine warrant for Circumſtances of worſhip as minute as this) will build upon probabilities, when it ſerves their turn. Becauſe it is not ſaid they roſe up, it is by conſequence gather'd
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:101809:65"/> they ſat ſtill. If they did, it was not our manner of ſitting, but another. If they had ſate as we, yet this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample is no more obligatory, than it is to other Circumſtances of the ſame Inſtitution. Yet through all theſe If's, and Conſequences, and Suppoſitions, they conclude to the expedience, if not to the neceſſity of a <hi>ſignificant Ceremony,</hi> though in us they call it <hi>Superſtition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The lifting up the hand at the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, the laying the hand upon the Book in ſwearing and other like Ceremonies, have been objected to them by others, I urge not that, but add another Inſtance whereby it will plainly appear, that many of the N. C<hi rend="sup">ts</hi>. though they ſuſpect ſo much <hi>ſuperſtition</hi> in a ſignificant Ceremony, yet can themſelves allow and urge the uſe of a Ceremony, and that in a Religious matter, and becauſe it is ſignificant, although the particular
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:101809:66"/> Ceremony be no where in Scripture commanded.</p>
            <p>They who have endeavour'd to<note place="margin">Sect. 15.</note> ſettle <hi>Presbyterated</hi> and <hi>Aſſociated Churches,</hi> have determin'd to do it by way of <hi>Covenant,</hi> ſo conſenting to be a Member of ſuch a Church. The Agreement of the Aſſociated Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es in <hi>Worceſterſhire,</hi> will give us light in this thing; who thus expreſs themſelves. <hi>Becauſe Miniſters ſhould</hi>
               <note place="margin">Agreement of the Aſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciated Churches in <hi>Worce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterſh. §. 18.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>have a particular knowledge of their Charge, which now is uncertain, and for divers other reaſons propounded and deba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted among us; We judge it very fit, if not of neceſſity, to deſire a more expreſs ſignification of our peoples conſent, to our Miniſtry and Miniſterial actions, and in particular to ſubmit to this diſcipline, as the members of that particular Church.</hi> Afterwards they tell us in what form of words they require this conſent to be given.</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:101809:66"/>I do conſent to be a Member of the particular Church of Chriſt at—whereof—Teacher, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>The reaſons why this was requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Baxter</hi> gives in his Explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that Agreement, not as his<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> own, but as thoſe that mov'd the <hi>Aſſociation</hi> to make that determinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The reaſons are Twelve. In all which there is not ſo much as a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of a divine Inſtitution, nay it is confeſſed in the Preface, <hi>that the ſign it ſelf of this conſent is not particularly determin'd;</hi> and M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Baxter</hi> after the reaſons adds this <hi>Memorandum: Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member yet that I maintain, that God does in Scripture require, only conſent ſignified</hi> (a thing which I do not now debate) <hi>but hath not tyed us to this or that parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular ſign, for ſignifying it, but having given us general Rules, that all things be done to Edification, decently,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>he hath left it to humane prudence to determine of
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:101809:67"/> the particular ſign, whether voice, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription,</hi> &amp;c. So then, ſuch a form of words is own'd to be a ſign ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying conſent. It is alſo own'd a ſign requir'd only upon General Rules of Scripture. What unpardonable crime is it then, if the <hi>Church of England</hi> agree upon ſome Ceremonies ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant, by virtue of the ſame general Rules, of Edification and Decency? In which Caſes if private men will be ſo wiſe as to abound in their own ſenſe, whether or no ſuch things be decent and edifying, the ſame M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Baxter</hi> hath determin'd the Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſy in the ſame place: where though he aſſert, that the Paſtors are to conſult with the people about the convenience; yet he poſitively con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes: <hi>That people are to obey the deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of their guides.</hi> And how now comes it to paſs that the power which they in their times aſſum'd, ſhould be denied the <hi>Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:101809:67"/> viz.</hi> Power and Authority to appoint ſignificant Ceremonies?</p>
            <p>If they will diſtinguiſh between Diſcipline and Worſhip, and allow a ſignificant Ceremony in that, but not in this, I reply, that in their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions for Diſcipline about M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Hookers</hi> time, that Axiome of theirs [<hi>Nothing ought to be eſtabliſhed in the Church, which is not commanded by the word of God</hi>] was applied to Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline as well as worſhip, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ. Pol.</hi> Lib. 3. Sect. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Degrees in the Univerſities, ſundry Church-Offices and Dignities were ſtruck at.</hi> Yea, they did affirm, that the <hi>Diſcipline was no ſmall part of the Goſpel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Survey of the preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Holy Diſciplin. <hi>p. 440.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>that without this Diſcipline there can be no right Religion, that they who reject the Diſcipline refuſe to have Chriſt reign over them.</hi> However it is clear, A ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant Ceremony becauſe allowed in Diſcipline, is not in the Nature of the thing unlawful. Nor does it deſerve the name of a Sacrament properly
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:101809:68"/> ſo called. Nor does the <hi>Church of England</hi> deſerve to be upbraided with <hi>ſuperſtition</hi> becauſe of ſuch appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p>If theſe grounds be firm and good, I conclude that the <hi>Rites</hi> and <hi>Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies</hi> of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> unleſs they be either burdenſome in their Number, or requir'd as ſomewhat in nature and kind, greater and more neceſſary than things <hi>Indifferent,</hi> are not faulty or <hi>ſuperſtitious.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Both which Caſes deſerve Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration.</p>
            <p>1. If our Rites be in their nature<note place="margin">Sect. 16.</note> Innocent, no man hath reaſon to find fault with their Number. The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pilers of our <hi>Liturgy</hi> have been aware, that an Objection might be here made, and have taken care to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the ſcruple. <hi>Some Ceremonies are</hi>
               <note place="margin">Preface to the Liturgy, of Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies.</note> 
               <hi>put away, becauſe the great exceſs and multitude of them hath ſo increas'd in theſe latter days, that the burden of them
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:101809:68"/> was intolerable, whereof</hi> St. Auſtin <hi>in his time complain'd,</hi> &amp;c. This our <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive multitude was ſo great, and many of them ſo dark, that they did more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found and darken, than declare and ſet forth Chriſts benefits to us.</hi> That Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint of St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> is in his Epiſtle to <hi>Januarius,</hi> where he acknowledges.<note place="margin">Aug. Janu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ario Ep. 119.</note> 
               <hi>Quamvis enim ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> hoc inveniri poſſit, quomodo contra fidem ſint; ipſam tamen Religionem, quam, pauciſſimis &amp; mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtiſſimis celebrationum ſacramentis, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſericordia Dei eſſe liberam voluit; ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libus oneribus premunt, ut tolerabilior ſit conditio Judaeorum. Admit that ſuch obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances be not againſt the Goſpel; yet in as much as the Merciful God would have Religion free from the burden of many Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies; they have ſo clog'd it with bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſome ſervices, that the condition of the Jews was more tolerable than of Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans now adays.</hi> That there may be no ſuch Cauſe of Complaint among us, the <hi>Church of England</hi> hath been very
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:101809:69"/> moderate in this thing. Not ſo as to eſcape the ill will of her Adverſaries, when they were reſolv'd to find fault; for the Preface to the <hi>Directory</hi> complains of the <hi>many unprofitable and burdenſome Ceremonies, contain'd in the Liturgy, which occaſion'd much miſchief:</hi> yet in cool blood ſome of the party are conſtrain'd to acknowledge <hi>the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Diſc. of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgies, <hi>p. 91.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>number of Ceremonies retain'd in our Church, pretending to any legal Authority, but ſmall. The Surplice, and Croſs, and Kneeling at Sacrament are we think all.</hi> And they do us much wrong if they refuſe this acknowledgment. For a great number of obſervations which obtain in the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> in the Celebration of the Sacraments (which from their number of <hi>ſeven</hi> we have reduc'd to <hi>Two</hi>) and in other parts of Divine Worſhip, have no place in the <hi>Church of England,</hi> leſt they ſhould divert the minds of men from worſhipping God in ſpirit and truth.
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:101809:69"/> Ceremonies harmleſs in themſelves may yet be hurtful in reſpect of their number, therefore hath our Church abrogated a great number of Saints<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>days and other like Cuſtoms, as M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ. Pol.</hi> lib. 4. Sec. 14.</note> 
               <hi>Hooker</hi> hath obſerved.</p>
            <p>Wherefore ſuch is the preſent ſtate of our Church, that we may ſecurely defy our Adverſaries in this matter, if it were as eaſy to cure their Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies of what may be, as to anſwer their objections againſt what is eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed. But here they make difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Though our preſent Number of Ceremonies be but ſmall, yet they raiſe a doubt, how far a Church may go; how many Ceremonies may be eſtabliſh'd, before the number be bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſome. Where is the <hi>Maximum quod non,</hi> and the <hi>Minimum quod ſic</hi> of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition. This is thought a great Argument why no Ceremonies, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond what are of direct neceſſity) ſhould be impoſed; becauſe of the<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bagſhaw</hi>'s Two great Queries, <hi>p. 10.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Impoſſibility to fix a point, where the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſer
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:101809:70"/> will ſtop. For do but once grant that the Magiſtrate hath power to impoſe, and then we ly at his mercy how far he will go.</hi> And they who allow our preſent number to be but ſmall, yet think them too many, becauſe, <hi>though there</hi>
               <note place="margin">Diſcourſe of Liturgies, <hi>p. 91.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>be no more Ceremonies eſtabliſhed by law as yet, there are many probationers, and they can ſee no reaſon, but the Churches power if allowed to appoint any (ſave on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuch, without which the ſervice of God, would apparently to all rational men, be perform'd indecently and diſorderly) may appoint Hundreds.</hi> It is alſo one of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Baxters</hi> reaſons, againſt the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing Croſſing, and the Surplice, <hi>&amp;c. When we once begin to let in Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Baxter</hi> Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>put. of Ch. Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>p. 477.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Mystical Rites, we ſhall never know where to ſtop, or make an end. On the ſame ground, that one age invents three or four, the next think they may add as many: and ſo it will grow to be a point of devotion, to add a new Ceremony (as at</hi> Rome <hi>it hath done) till we have more than we well know what to do with.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="117" facs="tcp:101809:70"/>
            <p>I anſwer. The Writings of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raliſts are not thought defective, though, when they have given Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Rules for Temperance, that men may not drink till they diſable their Reaſon, and impair their health, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they do not deſcend particularly to determine how many Glaſſes a man may drink, and preciſely to ſay, ſuch a draught makes him Intemperate. Nor did M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Chillingworth</hi> think, he was wanting to his Adverſary, who counted it <hi>prodigiouſly ſtrange, that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chillingw.</hi> Religion of Proteſt. &amp;c. <hi>p. 128, 129.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>could not be induc'd to give in a particular Catalogue of points Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal,</hi> when he calls it an <hi>Unreaſonable demand, becauſe variety of Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces makes it impoſſible to ſet down an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act Catalogue of them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I think I may have as much rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, to reckon it no Imperfection in this diſcourſe, if I do not venture pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually to determine, how great a number of Ceremonies may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired,
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:101809:71"/> before we come at <hi>Supersti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> When the number becomes ſo great that the ſhadow darkens the ſubſtance: When the ſubſtantial ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God, which ſhould be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in ſpirit and truth, is preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dic'd by the attendance that is given to the outward Ceremony: when the uſe of the means renders us unca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable to obtain the end; then does it riſe to that exceſſive multitude of which our Church ſpeaks. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the uſe of our liberty in other lawful things, cannot be fix'd in an Indiviſible point, but alters accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the various Circumſtances of times, and perſons, and conditions, and relations of men; therefore no wiſe man will give one particular determinate rule, which ſhall oblige equally in all Caſes.</p>
            <p>In like manner as our Church reckons Ceremonies Indifferent, ſo at the ſame time are they concluded
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:101809:71"/> alterable, and it is acknowledged, that <hi>upon weighty and important conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Preface to the Liturgy.</note> 
               <hi>according to the various exigency of times and occaſions, ſuch changes and alterations ſhould be made therein, as to thoſe in place of Authority ſhould from time to time ſeem either neceſſary or expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient.</hi> And here ſure muſt the thing reſt. It muſt be left to the prudence of our Governours. If they ſhall im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe any thing in which the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of people are not ſatisfied; If in truth it ſhall be believed that the number of Ceremonies enjoin'd is ſo great, that the means diſſerve the end; that what is ordain'd as an help to Piety and Devotion, does rather hinder it: theſe perſons ſo diſſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed about the number, are in the ſame caſe with thoſe who are diſſatisfied about the nature of an Injunction. If they ſcruple without cauſe, and are not duly inform'd, their ſcruples do not render the Injunction unlawful in
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:101809:72"/> it ſelf. Nevertheleſs, the Doctrine of our Church does not encourage them to act againſt their Conſciences, they muſt peaceably ſuffer where they cannot act. No doubt, but it is poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Church-Governours (who a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us do not pretend to Infallibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity) may in ſome things be miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken: Yet ſuch things as theſe muſt be left to their determination. For is it not ſo elſewhere? There may be too many Ale-Houſes in a Town, and it may be difficult to determine exactly how many are ſufficient, and where the number will exceed, but is it therefore unlawful for the Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to licence any? There may be in a Countrey, or Town, Pariſhes too many for the Maintenance, or too few for the people, and it may be difficult for Authority to know exactly how many are needful and convenient; Shall there be therefore no diviſion made into ſeveral, for
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:101809:72"/> fear leſt there ſhould be too many or too few? What if there be the ſame difficulty in adjuſting the true num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Ceremonies? yet in as much as it is neceſſary there ſhould be ſome, becauſe elſe Religion in the ſubſtance would ſuffer and decay; therefore is it alſo lawful for our Governours to make a determination in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            <p>The Determination of which num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber muſt proceed upon the ſame Rules of Decency, Order, and Edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, which give a law to the kind and nature of Ceremonies. And in this General may men reſt ſatisfied till the number ſhall grow doubtful. Then it will concern private perſons to take heed as to their own practice, that the Ceremony do not devour the ſubſtance. But becauſe at preſent there is no reaſonable Cauſe to fear; becauſe the Ceremonies that are now requir'd are ſo few, that no man may
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:101809:73"/> without peeviſhneſs quarrel at their number, if they be Innocent in their nature and uſe, therefore I return from this digreſſion to conſider that in the next place.</p>
            <p>2. The Rites and Ceremonies of our <hi>Church</hi> are not required as things in their nature neceſſary, but <hi>Indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The uſe of the <hi>Croſs</hi> at Baptiſm is<note place="margin">Canon 30.</note> thus accounted for, as being <hi>purg'd from all Popiſh ſuperſtition and error, and reduc'd in the Church of</hi> England <hi>to the primary Inſtitution of it, upon thoſe true Rules of Doctrine concerning things</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different, <hi>which are conſonant to the word of God and the Judgment of all Antient Fathers,</hi> &amp;c. And upon the ſame Rules of Doctrine are our other Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies eſtabliſhed. For ſo the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face to the <hi>Liturgy</hi> expreſſes it. <hi>The Ceremonies that remain, are retain'd for a Godly Diſcipline and Order, which (up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on just cauſes) may be alter'd and chang'd,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:101809:73"/> and therefore are not to be eſteem'd equal with Gods Law.</hi> And the Preface that was made upon the laſt eſtabliſhment ſays. <hi>The particular forms of Divine Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and the Rites and Ceremonies appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be us'd therein, are things in their own Nature</hi> Indifferent <hi>and alterable, and ſo acknowledged.</hi> Words too plain to need a Comment, and lyable to no Objection that I can foreſee, unleſs one of theſe two things ſhall be reply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed both upon them, and all that hath hitherto been ſaid in this matter.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That ſome things are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd under the Notion of things <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different,</hi> which are not ſo.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Be it granted that ſome <hi>Indifferent</hi> things may be impos'd, yet it does not follow that all may, or that the things in controverſy may.</p>
            <p>We ſay, the things they ſcruple<note place="margin">Sect. 17.</note> are requir'd but as things <hi>Indifferent</hi> as indeed they are. They are not all ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied to think ſo of them. The time
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:101809:74"/> was, when <hi>T. C.</hi> did oppoſe our Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, not as <hi>unlawful,</hi> but as <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenient,</hi> as hath been already ſaid. And M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Aſh</hi> in the Epiſtle to his Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Sermon on M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Gataker,</hi> when he had named <hi>Cartwright,</hi> and <hi>Hilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſham,</hi> and <hi>Dod,</hi> &amp;c. he ſays of them, <hi>though theſe men diſlik'd the uſe of ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Ceremonies, yet they oppos'd their Tenents and practice, who ſeparated from the</hi> Church of England, <hi>condemning it and the Miniſtry of it as Antichriſtian.</hi> The ſeparation is, it ſeems, now ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanc'd, for there are men that reckon there is more <hi>ſuperstition</hi> among us, than was believ'd formerly, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſeparate farther from us. <hi>It is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied</hi>
               <note place="margin">Modeſt Diſc. of Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remon. p. 8.</note> now <hi>that theſe are things of Indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency to be us'd (as is requir'd) in the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God.</hi> And whereas it is ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed that we ſay that the Impoſition of Rulers makes <hi>Indifferent</hi> things ceaſe to be <hi>Indifferent,</hi> they anſwer. <hi>They are not Indifferent in the Judgment</hi>
               <note place="margin">Petition for Peace, p. 12.</note>
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:101809:74"/> 
               <hi>of Diſſenters, though they be ſo in ours.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exercit. a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout an O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pining Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſci. p. 80.</note> They think they have <hi>probable Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to judge it unlawful to Miniſter in a</hi> Surplice, <hi>to ſign with the ſign of the</hi> Croſs <hi>in</hi> Baptiſm, <hi>and to</hi> kneel <hi>in the Act of receiving the Lords Supper.</hi> Yea theſe things are ſo far from being <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different,</hi> that they are thought ſo Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful, as that becauſe of them peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſeparate from our Churches. For whatever reaſons may perſwade their Guides not to conform, yet the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſeparate from us, that they may not partake with our Ceremonies, or for a worſe reaſon.</p>
            <p>I could not altogether omit ſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary a part of my Diſcourſe, but becauſe it hath been ſo often ſaid, I paſs it in fewer words. <hi>Where no Law</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 4.</note> 
               <hi>is there is no Tranſgreſſion.</hi> That which is not forbid is not Unlawful. Are theſe Rites and Ceremonies forbid in the word of God? By what Text? perhaps by the <hi>ſecond Commandment,</hi> or
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:101809:75"/> by thoſe words of St. <hi>Matth. Teaching for Doctrine the Commandments of men:</hi> Ch. 15. or by the Text <hi>of Will-Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, 2 Coloſ.</hi> or becauſe <hi>we may not add to, nor diminiſh from the word of God, Deuteron.</hi> 4. Now becauſe the <hi>Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plice,</hi> and <hi>Croſs,</hi> and <hi>Kneeling,</hi> are not named in theſe Texts (as was upon occaſion ſaid before) therefore Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences muſt be drawn from them, and labour'd ſo long, till the Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion muſt hold as firm as confidence can make it. Becauſe the <hi>ſecond Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand</hi> forbids making and worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing graven Images, therefore all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices and Inventions of mans brain muſt have no place in Divine Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. <hi>Ergo,</hi> what? <hi>Ergo,</hi> rend the <hi>Surplice, &amp;c.</hi> As if the <hi>Baſon</hi> at the Desk were not as much the device of man as the <hi>Font,</hi> and the <hi>Directory</hi> were not as obnoxious as the <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If our Church did equal her com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:101809:75"/> to the word of God, then were ſhe guilty of adding to the word, and eſtabliſhing the Commands of men in the room of the Doctrines of God. If any accidents may bring our Rites within the compaſs of ſome general prohibitions, the Unlawfulneſs of them upon that account, will be to be conſider'd in what next follows. If they ſhall be denied <hi>Indifferent</hi> in their own Nature, and yet no one Text of Scripture can be produc'd that ſpeaks one word about them, they who ſhall ſo deny, do both bring an Unanſwerable prejudice againſt all the particular eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, made by the General Rules of prudence, whether by the <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians</hi> or <hi>Independents,</hi> and do alſo quite miſtake the nature of a thing <hi>Indifferent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If we deſcend to particular Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, I deſire to know, why the <hi>Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plice</hi> is not as Indifferent as a <hi>Gown</hi> or
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:101809:76"/> 
               <hi>Cloak.</hi> Not becauſe it is a white Garment, for then why are not Bands Unlawful? And where is the Text that forbids white more than black? Nor becauſe it is of ſuch a faſhion; for the Scripture gives no more directions for the ſhaping of a <hi>Cloak</hi> than a <hi>Surplice.</hi> Why then? Surely either becauſe it is thought <hi>decent</hi> or <hi>ſignificant,</hi> or becauſe it is <hi>appropriated to divine worſhip.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. If it be <hi>decent,</hi> then is it no Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour to think it ſo; then the Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical <hi>Canon, let all things be done decent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> juſtifies and maintains it. And is it not decent? Does nature teach ſo, to whom St. <hi>Paul</hi> appeals? We do<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.</note> not find any inbred ſhame, as if we did ſomewhat Unnatural in the uſe of it. Does <hi>Scripture</hi> pronounce it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comely? We cannot find it. There is no other Rule for Decency, but either common eſtimation, or the pleaſure of our Governours: for the
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:101809:76"/> latter we are ſecure, and ſet peeviſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs aſide, fear not being condemn'd by the former.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Peradventure it is thought <hi>ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificant,</hi> therefore not <hi>Indifferent.</hi> I anſwer: that a <hi>ſignificant Ceremony</hi> (if this ſhould be ſuch) only as ſuch, <hi>is not ſuperſtitious.</hi> But who told our men of ſcruples, that it is urg'd as ſignificant of Candor and Purity? By what <hi>Canon</hi> or <hi>Rubrick</hi> is any man oblig'd to have ſuch an Opinion of it? Whatever others, who may have a better Opinion of ſignificant Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, may think of it, he who is ſatisfied to wear it as a decent Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, tranſgreſſes no Law, if he think no more.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Is it unlawful and not <hi>Indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent,</hi> becauſe it is <hi>appropriated to Divine Service?</hi> This it ſeems is D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Collings</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exercit. of Opin. Conſc. p. 80.</note> 
               <hi>ſcruple,</hi> who thinks it <hi>Unlawful to wear any habit peculiarly appropriated to the worſhip of God.</hi> I wonder then how it
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:101809:77"/> can be lawful to lean on a Pulpit Cuſhion, or to uſe a Communion Cup, if the Church-Wardens ſhould be ſo <hi>ſuperſtitious</hi> as to lock them up and preſerve them from all other uſes. If there be any thing in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture that forbids the uſe of a Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon any of theſe accounts, ſomewhat will be offer'd worth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering, till then, we continue to believe it <hi>Indifferent</hi> and free from <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. Why is not <hi>Kneeling, &amp;c. Indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent?</hi> not becauſe it is a <hi>poſture,</hi> for ſo is <hi>ſitting,</hi> but becauſe it is ſuch a poſture. And what is it? A poſture us'd upon any <hi>ſuperſtitious Opinion?</hi> Let us know what that is. Is it ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected to ſignifie our Adoration of the Elements? The <hi>Declaration</hi> of our <hi>Liturgy</hi> delivers us from that ſuſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and authorizes us to reckon them pitifully Ignorant, or monſtrouſly Uncharitable, who after ſo plain a
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:101809:77"/> Declaration will ſuſpect it. What it ſignifies we there read. <hi>This Order</hi>
               <note place="margin">Order for Adminiſ H. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mun.</note> 
               <hi>is well meant for a ſignification of our hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and grateful acknowledgment of the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits of Chriſt, and for the avoiding of prophanation and diſorder.</hi> If it be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful to ſignify humility and thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, why do we at any time kneel or lift up our hands and eyes to Heaven? Or if it be unlawful to avoid prophanation and diſorder, then let St. <hi>Paul</hi> be reproved for ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.</note> things in Order in the Church of <hi>Corinth.</hi> Till I can find ſome Text that forbids Kneeling, or till I can be ſatisfied that ſome <hi>ſuperſtitious</hi> Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion gives occaſion to it, I muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue to reckon this alſo <hi>Indifferent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. And to the ſame purpoſe I ſay of the <hi>Croſs</hi> at <hi>Baptiſm.</hi> How <hi>ſupersti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſly</hi> the <hi>Papiſts</hi> uſe it, I ſhall have occaſion to ſay, but our uſe of it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to where in Scripture forbid, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it can be proved, that our <hi>30th</hi>
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:101809:78"/> 
               <hi>Canon</hi> (of which before) gives a falſe Account of it, unleſs there be ſome <hi>Popiſh</hi> (or other) <hi>ſuperſtition</hi> or error from which it is not ſufficiently purg'd, it remains in its nature <hi>Indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent.</hi> Our general Anſwer in all is, as before, <hi>Where no Law is, there is no Tranſgreſſion. What is not forbid, is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, is not Unlawful.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. There may be ſome who will<note place="margin">Sect. 18.</note> grant that ſome <hi>Indifferent</hi> things may be Impos'd, yet will not yield that our Ceremonies therefore may, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of ſome objections againſt them, which have not equal force againſt all matters <hi>Indifferent.</hi> Such are theſe two thought to be.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The caſe of Scandal and give<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing offence to weak Brethren.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe they have been abus'd among the Papiſts.</p>
            <p>I ſhould be aſham'd to mention theſe things where in the N. C<hi rend="sup">ts</hi>. have been ſo often anſwer'd, did I not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:101809:78"/> that till this be clear'd, the prejudice which I deſire to remove will ſtill remain; for if for theſe reaſons Conformity be Unlawful, then may it ſeem, that they who either im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe or practiſe it, have an undue opinion of that which is ſo unlawful, and that opinion ſhall be ſuſpected of <hi>ſuperſtition.</hi> I proceed therefore to ſay, If they who impoſe theſe Rites, did not in truth judge them expedient and decent in the worſhip of God, only becauſe they think them barely lawful, they urge them as believing many ſcrupulous minds will be offended at them, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they lay them as Snares, and take advantage to incommode and bring under a penalty, thoſe who ſcruple them; this might be called <hi>Tyranny,</hi> but not properly <hi>ſuperstition,</hi> and ſo would not rach our Caſe. I make not this ſuppoſition as if I would tempt any diſſatisfied man ſo
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:101809:79"/> to judge of them, for aſſuredly it is no leſs than a blaſpheming of Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, to think they enact Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity for this reaſon. But I find they who pretend to be diſſatisfied will thus ſuſpect. And M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Bagſhaw</hi> thus expreſſes it, <hi>Whoever obtrudes his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits</hi>
               <note place="margin">Two great Queries concerning things In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diff. <hi>p. II.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>upon others, who perhaps are not ſo well ſatisfied as he is; becomes impious to God, by invading his ſovereignty, and lording it over another mans Conſcience; and likewiſe injurious to men, by preſſing ſuch things as are only baits to the careleſs, and traps for the Conſcientious.</hi> Unleſs there be more hypocriſy than <hi>ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stition</hi> in our Governours, this cannot be the caſe, for they profeſs to have done that <hi>which to their beſt underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings</hi>
               <note place="margin">Preface to the Liturgy.</note> 
               <hi>they conceiv'd might moſt tend to the preſervation of peace and unity in the Church, the procuring of Reverence, and exciting of Devotion, in the publick wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, and the cutting off occaſion from them that ſeek occaſion of cavil or
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:101809:79"/> quarrel againſt the Liturgy of the Church.</hi> They have then impoſed nothing, but what they judg'd not only law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, but expedient; which Impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons being already prov'd <hi>Indifferent,</hi> unleſs the Circumſtances that attend them render them ſuch, may not be judg'd <hi>ſuperſtitious.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is therefore to be conſider'd, whether either of the two ſuſpicions now mention'd, be reaſon enough to charge our way of worſhip as <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1. Suppoſe the Governours of the Church do not err in eſteeming theſe things in their own nature <hi>Indifferent,</hi> yet ſay <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> in as much as they are offenſive to many Godly and Conſcientious men, they ought not to be impos'd; or if they be, it will be doubtful, whether the great opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion they have of ſuch matters, as to enjoin them notwithſtanding their offenſiveneſs, be not a <hi>ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious</hi> Opinion.</p>
            <pb n="136" facs="tcp:101809:80"/>
            <p>I anſwer. If the Act for Unifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity ſhould contradict thoſe Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of the Goſpel, that oblige us not to <hi>lay ſtumbling-blocks,</hi> nor <hi>give of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence to our weak Brother;</hi> in as much as <hi>giving offence</hi> and not <hi>walking chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably</hi> are the ſame thing, this proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure would be a treſpaſs againſt the ſecond Table, rather than the Firſt, would be <hi>uncharitableneſs</hi> rather than <hi>ſuperſtition.</hi> It will be replyed. Though directly it be an offence againſt our Neighbour, yet reductively it is againſt the Firſt Table, becauſe ſuch a practice is declarative of ſome un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due and <hi>ſuperſtitious</hi> Opinions of thoſe things which are ſo impos'd. Let it be added therefore. So long as pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate perſons are not determin'd by the Laws of their Superiors, it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns them warily to uſe their liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to take heed that their doing that which is lawful, may not tempt others to do the ſame thing, while
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:101809:80"/> they judge it unlawful, which is the offending of our Brother, of which St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks to the <hi>Romans</hi> and <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians,</hi> who only diſcourſes of what ought to be done in thoſe Caſes, where no lawful power had inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd, to determine them one way or other. For eating fleſh and letting it alone were both lawful, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main'd <hi>Indifferent</hi> in nature and uſe too: Now ſo long as the caſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains thus, the Law of not ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizing a weak Brother is a Moral Law, becauſe it is an inſtance of the great Law of <hi>loving our Neighbour as our ſelves,</hi> and <hi>doing to others as we would have them do to us,</hi> wherefore ſo far as it is practicable it obliges. But this may not be extended to diſob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige the ſubject from obeying his ſuperiours in lawful things, nor to diſable the Magiſtrate from making laws in things <hi>Indifferent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, it does not diſoblige the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject,
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:101809:81"/> becauſe the law of obedience to our Superiors being alſo a Moral Law, either we are at the ſame time oblig'd by two laws which contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict, or one muſt yield to the other. If wearing the <hi>Surplice</hi> offend, I muſt either diſobey the Magiſtrate, or of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend my Brother. Which then of theſe two muſt give place? Accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the N. C<hi rend="sup">ts</hi>. we muſt relinquiſh a certain Rule for that which is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain. What the Magiſtrate com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands is certain, it is alſo certain, that I am in my Conſcience reſolv'd of the lawfulneſs of that which is ſo Commanded (taking it abſtractly from its offenſiveneſs) If I muſt now demur in my obedience leſt I give offence, how ſhall I certainly know whether I offend or no? how ſhall I know how many I may offend? What aſſurance ſhall I have but my Non-Conformity may offend as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny on the other ſide? I ſhall now
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:101809:81"/> proceed by an uncertain Rule, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I know not whither it will carry me, and I am in a Caſe where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in one Moral Law muſt give place to another. Whereas upon our Principles things are fairly reconcile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. In matters undetermin'd by Law, where we are at our liberty, we muſt walk charitably and take heed that we give no offence, that our <hi>liberty become not a ſtumbling-block,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 8. 9.</note> this is the Moral Law, and this is Goſpel. But there is no Precept of the Goſpel that commands us to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obey our Superiors lawful com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands for an uncertain danger of giving offence. Wherefore when we practiſe Conformity in obedience to eſtabliſh'd Laws, although perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture we ſhould offend our weak Brother, yet do we not thereby de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare a <hi>ſuperſtitious</hi> Opinion of the Ceremonies we uſe. We may think our ſelves oblig'd to obey our Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:101809:82"/> in all lawful things, and yet not think of the <hi>Surplice</hi> or <hi>Croſs, &amp;c. more highly than we ought to think.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. And as it does not diſoblige the ſubject from Obedience, ſo neither may it be thought to diſable the Magiſtrate from making laws about things <hi>Indifferent.</hi> For if it did, it were not ſafe to make any laws about <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency</hi> and <hi>Order,</hi> becauſe the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate can never be ſecure, but his Determinations may be ſo croſs to the opinions of ſome of his ſubjects, as to make them <hi>offend</hi> if they obey. But it hath been already evinc'd, that the N. C<hi rend="sup">ts</hi>. yield the Magiſtrate a power to proceed according to the Rules of Chriſtian Prudence in go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning the Church: And the frame of the <hi>Directory,</hi> and the urging of the <hi>Covenant</hi> do ſufficiently aſſure us, that the hazard of <hi>ſcandalizing a weak Brother,</hi> was no reſtraint to an Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:101809:82"/> of the <hi>Lords and Commons.</hi> He who in his Conſcience thought there was no way of worſhip ſo Regular as that of the <hi>Church of England:</hi> He who thought he ſhould ſin if he ſhould conform to the <hi>Directory,</hi> was not thereby excus'd from <hi>ſequeſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> Yet I dare ſay, they would take it ill, if they ſhould be ſuſpected of <hi>ſuperſtition,</hi> of having an undue opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of their manner of Divine Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. And I cannot yet ſee why they, commanding men to receive the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament <hi>ſitting,</hi> when probably that would tempt ſome men not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it at all, did not as much <hi>offend their Brother,</hi> and did not as much declare that they had a <hi>ſuperſtitious</hi> opinion of ſuch <hi>ſitting,</hi> as the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands that now require <hi>Kneeling</hi> may be ſo interpreted.</p>
            <p>2. Nor does the ſecond ſcruple weigh much. Our Ceremonies are ſuppos'd to have been abus'd among
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:101809:83"/> the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and this is made a great Argument by the N. C<hi rend="sup">ts</hi>. why they ſhould not be retain'd. To this the Anſwer hath been ſo often given to this purpoſe, that by the ſame rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon our Churches may not be now us'd, nor our Bells which have been Chriſten'd, nor any thing retain'd that relates to Divine Worſhip, but what is of abſolute neceſſity, and is particularly commanded; that I dwell not here any farther than, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to my former Method, to give a Teſtimony how little this ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection ſignifies when it is made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them.</p>
            <p>It had been laid to <hi>T. C</hi>' s. charge, that he ſhould thus declaim againſt the <hi>Church of England.</hi> The <hi>Communion</hi>
               <note place="margin">Survey of the H. pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipl. <hi>p. 315, 316.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Book was taken out of the Maſs-Book, that it were better to conform our ſelves in outward things to the Turks than to the Papiſts. Whatſoever comes from the Pope which is Antichriſt, comes firſt from the
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:101809:83"/> Devil, &amp;c.</hi> In the time of this Rail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery it did chance to be laid to his charge, that their <hi>Diſciplinarian</hi> way did ſmell of <hi>Donatiſm</hi> and <hi>Anabaptiſm,</hi> and was a kind of <hi>Papiſm.</hi> Now what defence does he make? <hi>If amongſt the filth of their Hereſies</hi> (viz. <hi>the</hi> Papiſts, Donatiſts, <hi>and</hi> Anabaptiſts) <hi>there may be found any good thing (as it were a grain of good Corn in a great deal of Darnel) that we willingly receive, not as theirs, but as the Jews did the Holy Ark from the Philiſtins, whereof they were unjuſt Own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. Yea it may come to paſs that the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue of Satan may at ſome time have ſome one thing with more convenience than the Catholick Church of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our <hi>Liturgy</hi> is indeed taken from them, but as gold is purg'd from droſs. And there are divers things wherein we agree with them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is no crime to agree with them there, where they do not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agree with the word of God: And
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:101809:84"/> becauſe it is not hard to believe that running into a contrary extream, that an Averſation from what is In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent among them, does harden them in their Errors as much, yea a great deal more, than a retaining ſome Cuſtoms which may honeſtly be retain'd. If we do not ſymbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lize with them in the <hi>ſuperſtition</hi> of their Rites, there is no reaſon we ſhould be charg'd with <hi>ſuperſtition;</hi> becauſe we do not run a madding from them as far as we are able into another extream.</p>
            <p>This is that I had to ſay to the ſecond general Propoſition (which hath exceeded the proportion of the other, becauſe it was my chief de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign.) <hi>The Doctrines upon which the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity of the Church of England is eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed, are not ſuperſtitious Opinions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. <hi>The Opinions that are ſuperſtitious,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sect. 19.</note> 
               <hi>ſuch as are divers which obtain in the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>and elſewhere, are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:101809:84"/> by the Church of</hi> England. There are many differences between us and the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> and they are not all reducible to this Topick of <hi>ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition.</hi> There are Doctrines among them of other denominations, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they ſerve ſome ſecular Intereſt of profit, or pleaſure, or honour; ſo is it eaſy to evince, that the Doctrine of <hi>Purgatory,</hi> and <hi>Celibacy of Priests,</hi> and others are Doctrines of men who reckon <hi>gain</hi> their <hi>Godlineſs.</hi> The Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of <hi>Indulgences</hi> and <hi>Diſpenſations, &amp;c.</hi> does not only deſign profit, but together with other looſe Doctrines of <hi>Morality,</hi> makes a very eaſie way to Heaven, and ſo is ſenſual and pleaſurable. And the <hi>Supremacy</hi> of the <hi>Pope</hi> and exemption of <hi>Eccleſiaſticks</hi> from ſecular Juriſdiction, is a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Mundane greatneſs and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufferable Ambition. There may be a mixture of <hi>ſuperſtition</hi> in all or any of theſe, according as mens appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:101809:85"/> are concerning them. But there are other matters, wherein I give account of their <hi>ſuperſtition.</hi> Biſhop <hi>Morton</hi> hath comprehended this in three generals, wherein he does at the ſame time vindicate the <hi>Church of England,</hi> and condemn that of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Our Church in her Service-Book does</hi>
               <note place="margin">Preſentment of a Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matick. p. 14.</note> 
               <hi>make known to all the World, that ſhe does deteſt the ſuperſtition of the Romiſh Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, by condemning their ſuperſtitious Opinions.</hi> Firſt, <hi>In making them neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary parts of Gods Worſhip.</hi> Secondly, <hi>In aſcribing an efficacious ſanctity to them.</hi> Thirdly, <hi>By arrogating a meritorious condignity from them to themſelves.</hi> I need not reſtrain my diſcourſe to Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies only, be it in Ceremony or be it in ſubſtance; If I make it appear that they eſteem that a neceſſary part of Gods worſhip which ought not to be ſo eſteem'd, (and ſo for the other two) I ſhall conclude right when I charge them with <hi>ſuperſtition.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="147" facs="tcp:101809:85"/>
            <p>An Enumeration of particulars will be the beſt evidence in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. I therefore give Inſtances to ſhow that for theſe ſeveral reaſons the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> is guided by <hi>ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Opinions</hi> to <hi>ſuperſtitious practices,</hi> by which it will alſo appear that the <hi>Church of England</hi> does renounce thoſe practices, at leaſt if for other reaſons ſome of them be retain'd, yet the Opinion which is the original of their practice is diſowned by us.</p>
            <p>1. That opinion is <hi>ſuperſtitious</hi> whereby men judge and eſteem any uſages in Religion neceſſary when they are not ſo, or more neceſſary than indeed they are. When men advance any thing in the worſhip of God beyond its nature, judging that to be holy, and to have a relation to God which hath none, or to have a nearer relation than in truth it hath. <hi>Pius</hi> IV. in a <hi>Creed</hi> which he impos'd,<note place="margin">Oruphrius in Vit. Pii 4. p. (mihi) 384.</note> furniſhes us with ſufficient Inſtances.</p>
            <pb n="148" facs="tcp:101809:86"/>
            <p>When he had by his <hi>Diploma</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd and confirm'd all that was done at the <hi>Council of Trent,</hi> he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded to direct in what manner Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops ſhould be made.</p>
            <p>Then it follows. <hi>Hanc Fidei formu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam quam Epiſcopi deſignati profiterentur inſtituit.</hi> He appointed a <hi>certain Creed which all that were to be made Biſhops ſhould make profeſſion of.</hi> In the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of which Creed are theſe words. <hi>Hanc veram Catholicam fidem, extra quam nemo ſalvus eſſe poteſt ſponte profiteor,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>This true Catholick Faith, out of which no man can be ſaved, I wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly profeſs.</hi> Now among the <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denda,</hi> which he reckons, and obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges others to reckon neceſſary to Salvation, are ſuch as theſe. That there are <hi>ſeven Sacraments</hi> of the <hi>New-Teſtament properly ſo called, inſtituted by Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> The <hi>propitiatory Sacrifice of the Maſs, Tranſubſtantiation, Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, Invocation of Saints, worſhipping Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:101809:86"/> and Images;</hi> and leſt enough ſhould not be crowded into that Creed, it is added. <hi>Caetera item omnia à ſacroſanctâ Tridentinâ Synodo tradita, definita &amp; declarata indubitanter recipio at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> profiteor.</hi> All that was determin'd at the <hi>Council of Trent</hi> is to be receiv'd without ſcruple. This is the Faith without which (they ſay) no man can be ſaved.</p>
            <p>How theſe Opinions are rejected by our Church is too plain to need proof. It reſt to ſay, however other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe faulty and dangerous they are, this makes them <hi>ſuperſtitious,</hi> that they are made neceſſary, whereas indeed they are falſe. I mean not every thing eſtabliſhed by that <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Trent,</hi> but the Articles before-named, and divers other like things decreed in that Council.</p>
            <p>If the Intendment of this Eſſay were principally againſt the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> it would the leſs be an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſion,
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:101809:87"/> if the things now mention'd were ſeverally conſider'd, and their repugnancy to Scripture ſhown; but being deſign'd rather for the Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> and that for the ſake of thoſe who agree with us in rejecting theſe Doctrines, I am not willing to engage in all theſe Controverſies. I think it ſufficient to add another inſtance under this Head, and ſo convict them together of <hi>ſuperſtition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Trent</hi> does advance<note place="margin">Hiſtor. Concil. Trident. Seſſ. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Unwritten Traditions</hi> to an Authority <hi>equal with the word of God.</hi> When the queſtion is mov'd what are theſe Unwritten Traditions, their Authors diſtinguiſh between ſuch as are <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, Apoſtolical,</hi> and <hi>Eccleſiaſtical.</hi> Thoſe which they call Divine are in the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of <hi>Azorius,</hi> ſuch as theſe. <hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Azor. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitut. Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral. Part. 1. lib. 8. Cap. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Tranſubſtantiation, Invocation of Saints, worſhipping Images, Communion in one kind enough for Laicks,</hi> &amp;c. Whereas
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:101809:87"/> the queſtion may be again ask'd, how ſhall we know that theſe are Divine Traditions after ſome other Rules, <hi>Bellarmine</hi> wholly reſts it upon the<note place="margin">Bellarm. De Verbo Dei non ſcripto. Cap. 9.</note> Teſtimony of the <hi>Romiſh Church. Ex Teſtimonio hujus ſolius Eccleſiae ſumi poteſt Certum Argumentum ad probandum Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolicas Traditiones.</hi> From the <hi>Teſtimony of the alone Church of</hi> Rome <hi>may a man have a certain Argument to prove Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical Traditions.</hi> Which rule I ſuppoſe he intends for the aſſuring us of <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Traditions</hi> too: for ſo he had before join'd them. <hi>Aſſerimus in ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turis</hi>
               <note place="margin">Id. ibid. Cap. 3.</note> 
               <hi>non contineri Totam Doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam neceſſariam, ſive de fide ſive de mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus, &amp; proinde praeter verbum Dei ſcriptum requiri etiam verbum Dei non ſcriptum,</hi> i. e. <hi>Divinas &amp;. Apoſtolicas Traditiones. We aſſert that the ſcripture does not contain all neceſſary Doctrine, whether about Faith or manners, there is therefore moreover requir'd, Divine and Apostolical Tradition.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="152" facs="tcp:101809:88"/>
            <p>From theſe premiſes I argue to the <hi>ſuperſtition</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they practiſe in their Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and elſewhere upon <hi>ſuperſtiti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us opinions.</hi> The Devotion of the Jews<note place="margin">Iſai. 29.</note> is thus challeng'd, <hi>Their fear toward me is taught by the precept of men.</hi> The Meſſages which God Almighty ſent them by his Prophets, were not the Rule of their worſhip, but the Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of men were inſtead of the word of God. And this was their <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debitus cultus,</hi> their <hi>ſuperſtition:</hi> This Text the <hi>Septuagint</hi> tranſlate, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>In vain do they worſhip me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 15.</note> 
               <hi>teaching the commands of men and Doctrins.</hi> St. <hi>Matthew</hi> hath alter'd the ſite of one word, and there we read in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication to the Phariſees. <hi>In vain do they worſhip me teaching for Doctrines the Commands of men.</hi> The caſe to which this quotation is there apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, is their making the Fifth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment of none effect by their
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:101809:88"/> Tradition. That which God had made neceſſary by his Command [<hi>Honour thy Father and Mother</hi>] with that they diſpens'd. That which God had not made neceſſary by any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Declaration of his pleaſure, that was made neceſſary by their Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And this was their <hi>ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which the caſe of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> is but too parallel. They make the <hi>ſecond Command</hi> of none effect by their <hi>Tradition</hi> of <hi>worſhipping Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges.</hi> In other things they make that neceſſary which the written word of God hath not made ſo. Some of which Traditions if they be not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly contrary to the word of God, yet becauſe they are arrogantly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qualled, and commanded to be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved <hi>Pari pietatis affectu &amp; reverentiâ;</hi> the practices that flow from theſe Doctrines cannot be excus'd from <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition,</hi> as we now uſe the word
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:101809:89"/> (and as they, as well as we, define the thing) for an exceſs in Religion, whereby men worſhip God, after ſuch a manner as they ought not.</p>
            <p>2. The ſecond Account of their<note place="margin">Sect. 20.</note> 
               <hi>ſuperſtition</hi> is, that they aſcribe an <hi>Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacious ſanctity to their Ceremonies.</hi> Here alſo Inſtances will make it plain, both that they are thus chargeable, and that the <hi>Church of England</hi> does reject theſe Opinions.</p>
            <p>The Doctrine of <hi>Rome</hi> is, that the <hi>Croſs</hi> is to be worſhipped with the <hi>higheſt kind of worſhip. Crux Chriſti in</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aquin. ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia Pars qu. 25. Artic. 4.</note> 
               <hi>quâ Christus Crucifixus eſt, tum propter repraeſentationem, tum propter membrorum Christi contactum Latriâ adoranda est. Crucis vero Effigies in aliâ quâ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riâ priori tantum ratione Latriâ adoranda eſt. The Croſs whereon Chriſt was Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified is to be worſhipped with</hi> Latriâ, <hi>both becauſe of its repreſentation, and becauſe of its touching the Body of Chriſt. But the ſign of the Croſs elſewhere, is to be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:101809:89"/> only for the former reaſon,</hi> (which laſt words were well put in, for it would be a wonder indeed, if the ſign of the Croſs made at <hi>Rome,</hi> ſhould deſerve worſhip <hi>propter Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tactum.</hi>) This we contend is <hi>ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious,</hi> becauſe the Opinions they have of the Croſs are ſuch. For they aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribe ſuch Effects to the Croſs, which neither the word of God aſcribes to it, nor any mans reaſon without the help of feigned Miracles, or Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions (before accounted for) would expect from it. Take it in <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min</hi>'s words. 1<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 
               <hi>Tres ſunt Effectus Crucis</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bell. de Imagin. Sancto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum lib. 2. Cap. 30.</note> 
               <hi>mirabiles. Terret &amp; fugat Daemones: 2<hi rend="sup">o</hi> pellit morbos &amp; omnia mala: 3<hi rend="sup">o</hi> San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctificat ea quibus imprimitur.</hi> There are <hi>Three wonderful effects of the Croſs. Firſt, It frights and ſeares away the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil. Secondly, It drives away Diſeaſes and all Evils. Thirdly, It ſanctifies thoſe things upon which it is made.</hi> The firſt of theſe effects he aſcribes to it for
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:101809:90"/> Three Cauſes. <hi>Ex apprehenſione Dae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>ex Devotione hominis, ex Inſtituto Dei.</hi> From <hi>the apprehenſion of the Devil,</hi> from the <hi>Devotion of man,</hi> from the <hi>Inſtitution of God.</hi> So that they ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the appointment of God hath empowr'd the <hi>Croſs</hi> to ſcare the Devil. The power of ſanctifying that upon which the ſign of the Croſs is made, he makes parallel with the power which he ſuppoſes in Reliques. <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctificantur</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
               <hi>aliquo modo ii qui tangunt Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quias,</hi> which he hath the confidence to aſſert upon the Authority of the Fathers.</p>
            <p>Our 30<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>Canon</hi> (as hath been ſaid) rejects theſe <hi>ſuperſtitions and errors.</hi> Which <hi>ſuperſtition</hi> we therefore lay to their charge, becauſe they aſcribe an effect to a certain Cauſe, without a ſufficient warrant. That the ſign of the Croſs hath not naturally in it ſelf any power of ſanctifying or curing, <hi>Bellarmine</hi> can't but acknowledge.
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:101809:90"/> 
               <hi>Signum Crucis operatur mirabilia non ex</hi>
               <note place="margin">Id. ibid.</note> 
               <hi>virtute ſuâ naturali quam habet ut figura quaedam, ſed ut ſignum divinitus Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum. The ſign of the Croſs works wonders, not as a certain figure, by any natural virtue, but as a ſign appointed of God.</hi> Here is then <hi>ſuperſtition,</hi> to eſteem the ſign of the Croſs more holy than in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it is, to believe it to have ſuch a relation to God, which it can't be prov'd to have, to aſcribe to it a vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue which no ſyllable in the H. Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture declares to us. And who hath known the mind of God any farther than he hath been pleas'd to reveal it to us?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eſtius</hi> makes a little attempt to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver<note place="margin">Eſtius in ſentent. Tom. 3. Diſtinc. 37. Sec. 8.</note> ſuch like Ceremonies as this is from <hi>ſuperſtition. Si debito decenti<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do exſpectetur effectus aliquis à Deo, eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amſi naturali virtute haberi non poteſt, nulla eſt ſuperſtitio. If the effect be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected in a due and decent manner, though the cauſe cannot by any natural virtue
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:101809:91"/> produce it, it is no ſuperſtition.</hi> So, he ſays, the Church does conſecrate <hi>Salt</hi> and <hi>Holy-Water,</hi> &amp;c. becauſe <hi>Chriſt gave his Apoſtles power over unclean</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 10. Luke 10.</note> 
               <hi>Spirits, and power to tread on Serpents and Scorpions,</hi> &amp;c. which power he ſuppoſes ſtill to reſide in the Church. As <hi>Eliſha</hi> cur'd the waters with <hi>ſalt,</hi> as <hi>Chriſt</hi> cur'd blind Eyes with <hi>clay</hi> and <hi>ſpittle,</hi> in like manner, <hi>poteſtas exorci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zandi Daemones à Chriſto Apoſtolis tradita uſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> in hodiernum diem in Eccleſiâ perman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit. The power of caſting out Devils com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by Chriſt to his Apoſtles remains in the Church to this day.</hi> If we will take Forgeries and cheats for real miracles, the thing is proved. But if we ſhould be a little ſcrupulous, and require bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter proof of matter of fact, and till that be given, ſhould doubt whether the Apoſtles power of working Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles be tranſmitted to this age, we are then at a great loſs to ſolve the <hi>Phaenomenon,</hi> and to clear the uſe of
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:101809:91"/> the <hi>Croſs</hi> and <hi>holy water,</hi> &amp;c. from <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition.</hi> Whereas it is confeſſed, that the natural virtue of theſe Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies can't produce ſuch effects, it is alſo as plain, ſo far as the Word of God is our guide, that we have no ſufficient warrant to expect theſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternatural and extraordinary Events, becauſe there is no divine promiſe annex'd to the uſe of theſe things.</p>
            <p>Of the ſame nature is that Doctrine that the Sacraments confer Grace, <hi>Ex opere Operato.</hi> The <hi>Council of Trent</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hiſtor. Conc. Trid. Seſſ. 7.</note> anathematizes them who ſay, <hi>per Sacramenta non conferri gratiam virtute miniſtrationis eorum, ſive ex opere operato.</hi> That the <hi>Sacraments do not confer grace by virtue of the very adminiſtration of them, or by the deed done.</hi> So <hi>Bellarmine</hi> begins his ſecond Book, <hi>De effectu Sacramentorum,</hi> with this enquiry. <hi>An ſacramenta novae legis ſint verae Cauſae juſtificationis ex opere operato.</hi> Whether <hi>the Sacraments of the Goſpel be true cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:101809:92"/> of Juſtification by virtue of the deed done.</hi> That they are ſo, and that they are thereby diſtinguiſhed from the Sacraments of the old Law, he offers to prove in the proceſs of that Book. In which though it be true, that he ſpeaks of Faith and Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance as diſpoſitions in the ſubject, to mollify the Opinion, yet there is no doubt but their Opinion is, that the Sacraments confer grace, however indiſpos'd the ſubject be. Which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by the abſolutions that are gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven upon Confeſſion, even there, where no Contrition ſhows it ſelf. According to the <hi>Jeſuit</hi>'s Doctrine,<note place="margin">Myſt. Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuitiſ. Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter 10. p. 145. 150. T. Bauny. Ibid.</note> 
               <hi>they ought not to be deny'd or delay'd abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, who continue in habitual ſias, againſt the laws of God, and nature, and the Church, though they diſcover not the leaſt hope of amendment.</hi> And <hi>Valentia</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termins <hi>that Contrition is not requiſite at all in order to obtain the principal effect of the Sacrament, nay on the contrary it is
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:101809:92"/> rather obſtructive.</hi> Yea <hi>Bellarmine</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf<note place="margin">Bellarm. de Imagin. Sanctorum lib. 2. Cap. 30.</note> elſewhere diſtinguiſhes between <hi>opus operatum,</hi> and <hi>opus operantis.</hi> When men pray for help againſt Diſeaſes, the effect does not infallibly follow, for this reaſon, <hi>quia tunc effectus non producitur ex opere operato, more Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentorum, ſed ex opere operantis.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is not produc'd <hi>by the deed done, as in the Sacraments, but ſuppoſes the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the doer.</hi> What they thus at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute to the <hi>Sacraments, Azorius</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to <hi>ſacramentals</hi> (though he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſes<note place="margin">Inſtitut. Moral. Part. 1. lib. 4. Cap. 11.</note> ſome Romaniſts are againſt him) he affirms that the very ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with <hi>Holy-Water</hi> without conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of the act of Repentance, does away venial ſins.</p>
            <p>How much our <hi>Church</hi> aſcribes to Sacraments, is plain. <hi>They are ſure</hi>
               <note place="margin">Artic. 25.</note> 
               <hi>witneſſes and effectual ſigns of Gods Grace and good will towards us, by which he does work inviſibly in us.</hi> But in the ſame Article it is declar'd againſt the <hi>Opus
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:101809:93"/> Operatum,</hi> for <hi>in ſuch only as worthily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the ſame, they have a wholeſome effect or operation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The dangerous Conſequences of this their Doctrine, eſpecially as their late Caſuiſts have improv'd it, I now exaggerate not. All that I would conclude hence is, that their worſhip of God in the Sacraments, becauſe it is built upon this opinion, is <hi>ſuperſtitious.</hi> God alone is the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of Grace, he conveys it into the hearts of men as he pleaſes: But no man hath reaſon to expect it by any other means than what God hath promiſed to bleſs. The Sacraments are of excellent uſe: But there is no promiſe extant that the bare receive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> whatever the diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition or indiſpoſition of the Recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be, ſhall produce this effect (and it is conferring grace <hi>in Adultis,</hi> that is now to be conſider'd.) Nay, we are aſſur'd that he who <hi>eats and
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:101809:93"/> drinks unworthily, eats and drinks dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to himſelf.</hi> Wherefore he who promiſes to himſelf, that which God hath not promis'd, he who expects grace upon theſe terms, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives the Sacrament upon an Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that the deed done (however it be done) will bring him into a ſtate of grace, is <hi>ſuperſtitious</hi> in ſo thinking and ſo doing.</p>
            <p>The Doctrine of <hi>Merit</hi> is another<note place="margin">Sect. 21. Bellarm. de Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat. lib. 9. Cap. 17.</note> 
               <hi>ſuperſtitious Opinion.</hi> If <hi>Bellarmine</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood it, this it is. <hi>Opera bona Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorum meritoria ſunt vitae aeternae ex con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digno, non ſolum ratione pacti &amp; accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis, ſed etiam ratione operis. The good works of juſt men do merit life eternal of condignity, not only becauſe of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of grace, but alſo from the nature of the works themſelves.</hi> Moreover be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the bare <hi>merit</hi> of good works, he affirms, that as a man may me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit a reward to himſelf, ſo he may make ſatisfaction for the releaſe and
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:101809:94"/> diſcharge of another. And this is the foundation of their doctrine of <hi>Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences. Extat Theſaurus aliquis in Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiâ qui ſit Indulgentiarum Fundamentum.</hi> For the making good of which he thus argues and proceeds.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Prima Propoſitio. In bonis actionibus</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bellarm. de Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent. lib. 1. Cap. 2.</note> 
               <hi>hominum Juſtorum duplex valor ſive pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium aſſignari poteſt, meriti,</hi> viz. <hi>&amp; ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactionis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secunda Propoſ. Opus bonum quâ parte meritorium eſt, non poteſt alii applicari, poteſt tamen quâ ſatisfactorium.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tertia Propoſ. Extat in Eccleſiâ The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaurus ſatisfactionum ex Chriſti paſſioni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus infinitus, qui nunquam exhauriri po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quarta Propoſ. Ad hunc Theſaurum ſuperfluentium ſatisfactionum pertinent etiam paſſiones B. Mariae Virginis, &amp; omnium aliorum ſanctorum qui plus paſſi ſunt quam eorum peccata requirerent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That is in ſhort. <hi>Together with the infinite value of the ſatisfactory ſufferings
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:101809:94"/> of our Saviour, The ſufferings of the B. Virgin</hi> Mary <hi>and all other Saints, who have ſuffer'd more than their ſins requir'd, are to be join'd, by which as they have merited to themſelves, ſo have they ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied for others.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How much this diſhonours the Undertakings of our B. Saviour, and for what other reaſons we explode the Doctrine of <hi>Merit,</hi> and the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendage of <hi>ſatisfaction,</hi> and <hi>Indulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> I have not now to ſay. The <hi>ſuperſtition</hi> of theſe Opinions is now to be conſider'd.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bellarmin</hi>'s Controverſies would not have deſerv'd the Character gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven them by <hi>Albertus Hungerus,</hi> in his approbation prefix'd to the <hi>Firſt Tome,</hi> viz. <hi>Integerrimum, pulcherrimum abſolutiſſimum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Controverſiarum omnium corpus,</hi> A moſt <hi>Entire and Compleat bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Controverſies;</hi> if he had balk't any of the Doctrines currant at <hi>Rome.</hi> So he muſt write when he
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:101809:95"/> pleads for a party; but I think it no very difficult task, to find ſome ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgments, even in thoſe ſame Books of Controverſies, which would greatly weaken moſt of the things in difference between us,<note place="margin">Bellarm. de Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat. lib. 5. Cap. 7.</note> which he would eſtabliſh. In this of <hi>Merit,</hi> who hath not heard of that famous reſolution of his: <hi>Propter incertitudinem propriae Juſtitiae &amp; pericu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum inanis gloriae, Tutiſſimum eſt fiduciam totam in ſolâ Dei miſericordiâ &amp; benigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate reponere.</hi> Becauſe of the <hi>Uncertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of our own righteouſneſs, and the danger of vain glory, It is moſt ſafe to put our whole confidence only in the mercy and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>—<hi>Siſic Omnia dixiſſet</hi>—</q>
            <p>How well does this agree with what we ſay in our Office of the <hi>H. Communion! We do not preſume to come
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:101809:95"/> to this thy Table, O Merciful Lord, truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in our own righteouſneſs, but in thy ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold and great Mercies,</hi> &amp;c. And with our 12 <hi>Article. Good works which are the fruits of Faith, and follow after Juſtification, cannot put away our ſins, and endure the ſeverity of Gods Judgment.</hi> We will join againſt the <hi>Antinomians,</hi> and with great zeal aſſert the <hi>neceſſity</hi> of good works, if the <hi>merit</hi> of them may be excluded, but that we can't but charge with <hi>ſuperſtition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He who gives Alms, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> does a good work acceptable to God by Jeſus Chriſt; but he who opines, he thereby merits the favour of God (any otherwiſe than becauſe God has promis'd to accept ſuch ſervices) He who apprehends ſuch a worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in what he does, as that for its own ſake he may expect to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive ſome reward, becauſe there is ſome proportion and equality in it, <hi>ad praemium vitae aeternae,</hi> as <hi>Bellarmine</hi>
               <pb n="168" facs="tcp:101809:96"/> ſpeaks: He who deſigns to oblige Almighty God by his good works; hath a proud conceit of himſelf, who when he hath done all he can, <hi>is but an Unprofitable ſervant;</hi> and he has a falſe and undue Opinion of God, to think a man may be profitable to God, as men may be one to another. Therefore are theſe ſervices <hi>ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious,</hi> becauſe they are perform'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on falſe and undue Opinions, and he who thus worſhips God, does that which is not requir'd at his hands.</p>
            <p>If theſe things wanted evidence, I might add their works of <hi>ſupereroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> their <hi>Auſterities and penances,</hi> ſo far as they apprehend a Merit <hi>in Opere Operato.</hi> Alſo other things might have a place in this Argument, and might range by themſelves, if they be not reducible to any of Biſhop <hi>Mortons</hi> general heads. Such as are, <hi>Their publick Prayers in the Church, in a Tongue not underſtood of the people.</hi> Their
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:101809:96"/> requiring and uſing ſuch a vaſt num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Ceremonies, which by their great exceſs and multitude become a burden intolerable (as the Preface to our <hi>Liturgy</hi> acknowledges) Theſe and ſuch like things can't be excus'd from <hi>ſuperſtition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Together with theſe I might add a number of obſervations which are neither proper to <hi>Popery,</hi> nor indeed to the <hi>Chriſtian Religion,</hi> but are ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd all over the World. Such as St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> means when he complains of <hi>Millia inaniſſimarum obſervationum, &amp;c.</hi> and ſuch as <hi>Aquinas</hi> comprehends, when he makes divers kinds of <hi>ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition, Divinationes &amp; varia obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onum genera.</hi> Of which Cuſtoms <hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metaniſm</hi> and <hi>Gentiliſm</hi> are very full. But having given account of theſe before, I paſs them with this general acknowledgment.</p>
            <p>Whatever we do upon a Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous account, where Religion, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:101809:97"/> ſo called, ought not to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd; When any undue Opinion of God excites us to any action, when we exerciſe our ſelves in that, which may be deſervedly called, <hi>Indebitus Dei Cultus,</hi> when we think God is pleas'd with ſuch a manner of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance, which does not pleaſe him; as it does well agree with the Import of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (an <hi>over-timor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> and <hi>ſervile apprehenſion</hi> of the <hi>Deity</hi>) ſo may it properly be called <hi>ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But in as much as it is very evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that the <hi>ſuperſtitious</hi> Opinions of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> are rejected by the <hi>Church of England,</hi> in as much as it can't be prov'd, that any of our ſervice is enjoin'd upon any other Opinion equally <hi>ſuperſtitious;</hi> we conclude, there is wrong done us, when <hi>ſuperſtition</hi> is laid to our charge. Yea, if peradventure ſome of our Church ſhould have private Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:101809:97"/> of their own, that might render their particular practices <hi>ſuperſtitious,</hi> yet this is enough to deliver our ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice from the Imputation, and in this we perſiſt as our juſt Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>There is no <hi>Canon</hi> nor <hi>Rubrick,</hi> no <hi>Article</hi> nor <hi>Injunction</hi> that obliges any within our Communion to any <hi>ſuperſtitious Opinion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>4. <hi>Propoſition.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sect. 22.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>There are ſuperſtitious Omiſſions of which men may be guilty; and that then, when they ſeem to have a great zeal a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Burges</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>join'd Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face, p. 64.</note> 
               <hi>ſuperſtition.</hi> It was laid to the N. C<hi rend="sup">ts</hi>. charge in <hi>King James</hi> his time, that they were guilty of <hi>negative ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition.</hi> A phraſe cavil'd at by thoſe who reply upon Biſhop <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> but D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Burges</hi> has ſufficiently vindicated it, and commends them to their friend <hi>Ames,</hi> who compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hends it in his definition of <hi>ſuperſtition.</hi> For when he had defin'd it to be an
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:101809:98"/> exceſs of Religion; He adds, <hi>cujuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modi</hi>
               <note place="margin">Medul. Theolog. lib. 2. Cap. 13.</note> 
               <hi>exceſſus non tantum eſt in exercitiis poſitivis, ſed etiam in Abſtinentiâ à qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rundam rerum uſu, ut àcibis. This exceſs of Religion is not only in what we poſitively do, but may be alſo, in what we abſtain from, as Meats.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>True it is, that <hi>ſuperſtition</hi> is an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, as it hath been defin'd, yet the defect in the practice may be <hi>ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious,</hi> becauſe it may proceed from exceſs in the Opinion. For if a <hi>ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious</hi> Opinion be the reaſon why men abſtain from the uſe of a Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, that abſtinence is as properly <hi>ſuperſtitious,</hi> as the uſe of it upon a <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious</hi> Opinion can be. <hi>My Lord Bacon</hi> ſays well and wiſely. <hi>There is</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bacon</hi> Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay of Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition.</note> 
               <hi>a ſuperſtition in avoiding ſuperſtition, when men think to do beſt, if they go fartheſt from the ſuperſtition formerly received.</hi> There is a <hi>ſuperſtitious fearfulneſs</hi> in ſome men, of which St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains<note place="margin">Auguſt. Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuario. Ep. 118.</note> thus. <hi>Senſi ſaepe dolens &amp; gemens,
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:101809:98"/> multas infirmorum perturbationes fieri, per quorundam fratrum contentioſam obstina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem &amp; ſuperstitioſam timiditatem, qui in rebus hujuſmodi, quae ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſacrae ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turae Authoritate ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Univerſalis Eccleſiae traditione ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> vitae corrigendae utilitate ad certum poſſunt terminum pervenire, tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum quia ſubeſt qualiſcun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ratiocinatio, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitantis qut quia in vuâ patriâ ſic ipſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuevit, aut quia ibi vidit, ubi peregrina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem ſuam quò remotiorem à ſuis eò docti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orem factam putant, tam litigioſas exci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant quaeſtiones, ut niſi quod ipſi faciunt nihil rectum exiſtimant.</hi> Words which by a little alteration and paraphraſe are but too accommodate to the caſe of our preſent Diſſenters.</p>
            <p>
               <q>To the grief of my Soul I have often obſerv'd, how weak and ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous minds have been miſerably perplex'd in matters of Religion, by the contentious obſtinacy and <hi>ſuperſtitious fearfulneſs</hi> of ſome who ſeem to be very Godly men. Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:101809:99"/> ariſe in matters Indifferent and alterable in their own natures; ſuch as the H. Scripture hath not any where particularly determin'd; nor hath any tradition of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Church fix'd them in one certain courſe; nor can it be ſaid, that for the bettering the lives of men, it muſt be thus, and may not be ſo: yet there are Jealouſies and ſcruples in their minds, it may be they remember it otherwiſe in their times, and where they have lived. It may be they have been as far as <hi>Scotland, Amſterdam,</hi> or <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neva,</hi> and have a greater opinion of what is done abroad: For one reaſon or other they are litigious and troubleſome, and think no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing well done, but what they do themſelves.</q>
            </p>
            <p>From this ſcrupuloſity are men apt to call any thing into queſtion, and for fear leſt they ſhould err on
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:101809:99"/> one hand, and run into <hi>ſuperſtition</hi> and <hi>Popery;</hi> they run as far on the other; and their Omiſſions are as <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perstitious,</hi> as they fear'd their practice would have been.</p>
            <p>Such was the caſe of the <hi>Jews,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Machab. 2.</note> when they were aſſaulted by their Enemies on the <hi>Sabbath day;</hi> rather than violate the <hi>Sabbath</hi> by defending themſelves, they tamely ſuffer'd themſelves to be deſtroyed. The law of ſelf-preſervation could not perſwade them to any reſiſtance, and if <hi>Mattathias</hi> had not been wiſer than the reſt, they might all have pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed.</p>
            <p>Such alſo was the <hi>ſuperſtition</hi> of the<note place="margin">Knol. <hi>Turk. Hiſtory.</hi>
               </note> Souldiers in <hi>Sfetigrade,</hi> when <hi>Amurath</hi> beſieg'd it (<hi>An.</hi> 1449.) A Traytor in the City had caſt <hi>a dead dog,</hi> into the only Well which ſupplyed the City with Water: which when it was eſpied in the Morning by the Souldiers, no Importunity could per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:101809:100"/> them to drink of that Water which they reputed <hi>Unclean by a dogs Carcaſs;</hi> ſo was the Governour com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell'd to ſurrender the City.</p>
            <p>And ſuch ſurely was the conceit of that zealous man ſome while ſince among our ſelves, who cut out of his <hi>Bible,</hi> the <hi>Contents of the Chapters,</hi> and ſo would cut out the word of God it ſelf, that was on the other ſide of the page, rather than ſuffer any <hi>Humane mixture</hi> with the pure word of God.</p>
            <p>Whether the caſe of our N. C<hi rend="sup">ts</hi>. be not ſomewhat parallel, is now to be conſider'd. They ſuſpect <hi>ſuperſtition</hi> in the uſe of the <hi>Surplice</hi> and <hi>Croſs, &amp;c.</hi> and therefore Religiouſly ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain from them; but what if this Abſtinence alſo ſhould be <hi>ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous?</hi> If the Rites and Ceremonies of our Church be as they imagine, it muſt be, either becauſe we judge that <hi>lawful</hi> which is <hi>Unlawful,</hi> or that <hi>neceſſary</hi> which is but <hi>Indifferent,</hi> or
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:101809:100"/> becauſe theſe Ceremonies though granted in their own nature <hi>Indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent,</hi> yet by reaſon of ſome Accident that attends them, may not be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd, and may not be ſubmitted to if impos'd. All which things have already had their Conſideration, after all which I have not doubted to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that our Rites may be us'd without <hi>ſuperſtition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now I move a doubt on the other ſide, to which if they cannot give a better Anſwer than I am a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of, they can't excuſe themſelves from <hi>ſuperſtition.</hi> For what other rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons Conformity may be refus'd I now enquire not. If any refuſe it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they cannot wear a <hi>Surplice,</hi> or uſe the <hi>Croſs,</hi> and if any private per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons neglect the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, becauſe they cannot <hi>kneel</hi> as is commanded; I deſire to know for what reaſons they are not free to join with us in theſe Uſages.
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:101809:101"/> Either they think them lawful or Unlawful: If lawful, ſuch as may be ſubmitted to, and yet for ſome po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litick reſpects they will not ſubmit; this Abſtinence of theirs may be free from <hi>ſuperſtition,</hi> but ſome other way it will be as Unaccountable: For he who without violating his Conſcience can conform but will not, let him (if he can) excuſe his diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Powers which God hath ſet over him, let him (if he can) deliver himſelf from the Character of a contentious man.</p>
            <p>If without fraud or guile, there be a man who does not act becauſe he dare not, who is perſwaded in his Conſcience, he ſhould ſin againſt God, and do that which is Unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, if he ſhould wear a <hi>Surplice,</hi> &amp;c. This is the man whom I charge with <hi>ſuperſtition,</hi> becauſe he judges that <hi>Unlawful,</hi> which is <hi>Indifferent,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he proceeds upon a miſtake of
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:101809:101"/> the nature of things, becauſe a falſe opinion betrays him to this abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence. He declares hereby that he hath a wrong Notion and apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of God, when he thinks him diſpleas'd by ſuch an Action, againſt which the Scripture hath not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar'd his diſpleaſure. As men may teach for Doctrines the poſitive Commands of men, ſo may they alſo teach for Doctrines the prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of men; and this is <hi>adding to the word of God.</hi> And in this does <hi>Ames</hi> condition take place. <hi>In illâ Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinentiâ</hi>
               <note place="margin">Medul. Theol. prius.</note> 
               <hi>Honor aliquis ſingularis Deo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenditur.</hi> They conceit they Honour God by abſtaining from that which is no where forbidden. It is no where ſaid, neither in expreſs words, nor in any equivalent phraſe, That it is the will of God, no man ſhould wear a <hi>white Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> when he Miniſters in Divine Offices; that no man ſhould <hi>kneel</hi>
               <pb n="180" facs="tcp:101809:102"/> when he receives the Sacrament, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Wherefore what God hath cleanſed, why ſhould we call Common? Where is the man that hath Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to pronounce that Unclean, which God hath not ſo pronounc'd? The neceſſary uſe of theſe things when they are commanded, does not take away the <hi>Indifferency</hi> of their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and this delivers us from <hi>ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition:</hi> But to abſtain from them as <hi>Unlawful</hi> in their nature, does direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contradict the opinion of their <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differency,</hi> and leaves the men who ſo abſtain, under the guilt and bond of <hi>ſuperſtition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So may men find that at a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticle, which they are afraid to meet at Church. <hi>Superſtition</hi> lodges in the minds of men, and they who are inclin'd to it, may diſcover it when they ſit ſtill, as well as when they move. <hi>Touch not, taſt not, handle not,</hi> are not greater Indications of a
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:101809:102"/> 
               <hi>ſuperſtitious abſtinence,</hi> than are <hi>wear not, kneel not, Croſs not;</hi> when the Doctrine of theſe Ceremonies is known to be Innocent and allowa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Wherefore they who are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed afraid of <hi>ſuperſtition,</hi> who are afraid of mixing their own Inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons with the worſhip of God, and doing that which is not requir'd at their hands, are concern'd rightly to inform themſelves, in what they are commanded to do: And when they find that the H. Scripture hath no where forbid the uſe of the <hi>Surplice</hi> upon thoſe Terms upon which it is enjoin'd, (only the liberty which they themſelves had power to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, is by the Magiſtrate deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min'd for them, not lightly or wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonly, but for grave and weighty rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons) Let them not fear they ſhall <hi>tranſgreſs</hi> where there is <hi>no law.</hi> Let them not fear <hi>ſuperſtition</hi> in thoſe pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices to which they are induc'd by
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:101809:103"/> Opinions not <hi>ſuperſtitious.</hi> But on the other ſide let the fear be, leſt they make the way to Heaven ſtraiter than our Saviour hath made it. Leſt they ſcruple and condemn that which does not appear unlawful. Leſt they ſplit upon <hi>Scylla</hi> while they ſhun <hi>Charybdis.</hi> Leſt they run into <hi>ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> while they deſired to avoid it, and leſt an Innocent Ceremony ſcare them to an Unjuſtifyable Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
